<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The lands mourning, for vaine swearing: or The downe-fall of oathes Declaring how this land groneth vnder the burthen of this sinne, and of Gods fearefull iudgements that attend it. A sermon preached at Paules Crosse, the 11. of Iuly. 1613. By Abraham Gibson, Mr. of Arts.</title>
            <author>Gibson, Abraham, b. 1586 or 7.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1613</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 179 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 64 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A01691</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 11829</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S118374</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99853581</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99853581</idno>
            <idno type="VID">18971</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A01691)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 18971)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1100:05)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The lands mourning, for vaine swearing: or The downe-fall of oathes Declaring how this land groneth vnder the burthen of this sinne, and of Gods fearefull iudgements that attend it. A sermon preached at Paules Crosse, the 11. of Iuly. 1613. By Abraham Gibson, Mr. of Arts.</title>
                  <author>Gibson, Abraham, b. 1586 or 7.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 118 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by T. S[nodham] for Ralph Mab, and are to be solde in Paules Church-yard, at the signe of the Angell,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1613.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Swearing --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-03</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>Emma (Leeson) Huber</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>Emma (Leeson) Huber</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:18971:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:18971:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE LANDS Mourning, FOR vaine Swearing: OR The downe-fall of Oathes. Declaring how this Land groneth vnder the burthen of this Sinne, and of Gods fearefull Iudgements that attend it. A Sermon preached at <hi>Paules Croſſe,</hi> the 11. of Iuly. 1613. BY <hi>Abraham Gibſon,</hi> M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. of Arts.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed by <hi>T. S.</hi> for <hi>Ralph Mab,</hi> and are to be ſolde in <hi>Paules</hi> Church-yard, at the ſigne of the Angell. 1613.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:18971:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:18971:2"/>
            <p>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE SYR <hi>John Swinnarton,</hi> KNIGHT, <hi>Lord Maior</hi> of the renowned Citie of LONDON.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>AND</hi> To the right VVorſhipfull,<list>
                  <item>M<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> 
                     <hi>Edward Rotherum.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>M<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> 
                     <hi>Alexander Preſcot.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <hi>Sherifs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>WITH</hi> The reſt of the right VVorſhipfull ALDERMEN, <hi>AND</hi> Other worthy Citizens of <hi>London.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. G. <hi>Dedicateth theſe his poore Labours, which lately were of them</hi> moſt<list>
                  <item>Diligently attended.</item>
                  <item>Graciouſly accepted.</item>
                  <item>Earneſtly deſired.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:18971:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:18971:3"/>
            <head>TO The Chriſtian Reader, all Chriſtian Graces.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Hriſtian <hi>Reader,</hi> for my ſelfe al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready to be ſeene in the <hi>Preſſe,</hi> will be to ſome as great a wonder, as <hi>Saul</hi> among the <note place="margin">1 Sam. 19. 24.</note> 
               <hi>Prophets.</hi> I muſt confeſſe, that in regard of the ſmall number of my yeres, (being ſo few moneths aboue the age <note n="*" place="margin">24</note> required to our calling,) I might iuſtly haue incurred the cenſure of preſumption both to Preach at the <hi>Croſſe,</hi> and to
<pb facs="tcp:18971:4"/>
come into the <hi>Preſſe,</hi> had I not to the former beene inioyned by <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie,</hi> and to the latter preſſed by <hi>importunitie.</hi> After many de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nials I was forced to yeeld to the continuing <hi>requeſts</hi> (and no leſſe earneſt, then godlie) of ſuch Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable, Worſhipfull, and worthy intreaters: Whoſe liking thereof, had it beene no better then my owne, the place of <hi>Birth</hi> had bene the place of <hi>Burial;</hi> and the <hi>Croſſe</hi> had beene the <hi>Graue,</hi> wherein to leaue it. But the rather haue o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers deſires for publiſhing this <hi>Sermon,</hi> at length preuailed and ouercome me, becauſe the good ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptance, &amp; incouragement, which it had of the <hi>hearers</hi> giueth mee hope that ſome benefit may enſue to the <hi>Readers,</hi> and that it ſhall be profitable to ſome, hurtfull to
<pb facs="tcp:18971:4"/>
none. It layeth open a ſinne very dangerous and <hi>deteſtable;</hi> and yet (the more pitty) too com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon and <hi>cuſtomable.</hi> If here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by I may reclaime but one from it, I haue my reward: that is the one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly marke I ayme at, not <hi>affectation</hi> not <hi>oſtentation.</hi> Plaine it was in the <hi>Preaching,</hi> more plaine it is in the <hi>Printing:</hi> ſome <hi>Quotati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> I haue omitted, and interpoſed in the <hi>Margent,</hi> to the end it may no way be obſcure, but plaine to the plaineſt. Thus (with <hi>Wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome)</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pro. 9. 2. 5.</note> I haue prepared <hi>cheare</hi> for thy <hi>ſoule;</hi> and now (with her alſo) I inuite thee to <hi>eate</hi> of it. When I can prouide better thou ſhalt haue it. In the meane time <hi>accept</hi> this, and <hi>welcome</hi> to it. If thy <hi>ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macke</hi> be curious, it is not for thee: If otherwiſe, much good doe
<pb facs="tcp:18971:5"/>
it thee. If any good hereby re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dound to thy <hi>Soule,</hi> let God haue thy <hi>prayſe,</hi> and mee thy <hi>prayers.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Waldingfield parua. <hi>Suffolke.</hi>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Thine in Chriſt Ieſus, A. G.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:18971:5"/>
            <head>THE Lands Mourning, FOR <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>aine-Swearing. OR, THE DOWNE-FALL</hi> of OATHES.</head>
            <head>A Sermon preached at <hi>Paules-Croſſe,</hi> the 11. of <hi>Iuly.</hi> 1613.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>IEREM. 23. 10.</bibl>
               <q>Becauſe of <hi>OATHES,</hi> the Land mourneth.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ight Honourable, right Worſhipfull, and Well-beloued, Men, Brethren, and Fathers, if euer there were a time
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:18971:6"/>
when, if euer a place where, <hi>Gods Miniſters and Watch-men,</hi> as <hi>Eſay</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Eſay 56. 10.</note> calleth them; <hi>his Stewards and Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadours,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Tit. 1. 7. 2 Cor. 5. 20.</note> as <hi>Paul</hi> nameth them; <hi>his Angels and Meſſengers,</hi> as <note place="margin">Malach. 2. 7.</note> 
               <hi>Malachy</hi> tearmeth them, had need <hi>to cry aloud and not to ſpare,</hi> to ſpeak <note place="margin">Eſay 58. 1.</note> boldly and not to feare, <hi>to ſhew the people their tranſgreſſions, and to the Houſe of Iacob their ſinnes;</hi> then now is the time, here is the place: the time is now, in this our age, the place is here, in this our Land. That which the Heathen man ſpoke in former times, is much more veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied in theſe times: <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heſiod.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> Both Land and Sea is full of euill: ſuch generall forwardneſſe on the one ſide to that which is bad, ſuch frowardneſſe there is on the other ſide to that which is good; we may truly ſay with <hi>Paul, the dayes are euill.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Epheſ. 5. 16.</note> Notwithſtanding, the ſound of the Word hath gone into all the Land, the bright beames of the Goſpell
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:18971:6"/>
haue gloriouſly ſhined vpon vs, and the bels of <hi>Aaron</hi> beene long rung amongſt vs; yet how many proud <hi>Pharaohs,</hi> that doe not ſticke to ſay in their hearts, <hi>Who is the Lord that I ſhould heare his voyce?</hi> how many <note place="margin">Exod. 5. 2.</note> vngodly <hi>Ahabs,</hi> that haue <hi>ſolde themſelues to worke wickedneſſe in</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 Kings 21. 25.</note> 
               <hi>the ſight of the Lord?</hi> how many wicked <hi>Ieroboams,</hi> that <hi>cauſe others to ſinne?</hi> and, to vſe the Apoſtles <note place="margin">1 Kings 22. 52.</note> words, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <note place="margin">Rom. 1. 32.</note> not onely doe ſuch things them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, but <hi>fauour and delight in them that doe them?</hi> On the other ſide, how <hi>little is the Flocke of Chriſt?</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Luke 12. 32.</note> how few amongſt vs Faithfull, as <hi>Abraham</hi> was? Righteous, as <hi>Lot</hi> was? Zealous, as <hi>Ioſiah</hi> was? Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious, as <hi>Dauid</hi> was? True harted, as <hi>Ionathan</hi> was? Couragious, as <hi>Paul</hi> was? and Deuout as <hi>Cornelius</hi> was? Theſe, and ſuch like, are ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered to their Fathers; few, or none, are left of them: they are like <hi>the Summer gatherings,</hi> as <note place="margin">Micah. 7. 1.</note>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:18971:7"/>
               <hi>Micah</hi> ſpeaketh. <hi>This gate is ſtraite,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Mat. 7. 14.</note> 
               <hi>this way narrow, and few there be that finde it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>God hath offered vs his Spirit, but that wee haue quenched: hee hath ſent vs his Prophets, but them wee haue deſpiſed: hee hath giuen vs his Mercies, but theſe wee haue abuſed: hee hath warned vs by his Iudgements, but thoſe wee haue neglected. Sathan neuer more bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, <note place="margin">Reuel. 12. 12.</note> for his time is ſhort: Sinne ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſo common, as in theſe laſt dayes: men <hi>draw it with Cords,</hi> as <note place="margin">Eſay 5. 18.</note> 
               <hi>Eſay</hi> ſpeaketh: <hi>drinke it like water,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Iob 15. 16.</note> as <hi>Iob</hi> ſpeaketh: they lie, they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue, and ſleepe in it: and it is ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer to commit it then to reproue it. Gods Miniſters may ſay of this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as the Prophet, of <hi>Iſrael, From</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Eſay 1. 6.</note> 
               <hi>the ſole of the foote vnto the head, there is nothing whole therein, but wounds, and ſwelling, and ſores full of corruption.</hi> Wee may take vp the complaint of the Children in the Market place, <hi>Wee haue piped vnto</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Luke 7. 32.</note>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:18971:7"/>
               <hi>you, and yee haue not daunced; wee haue mourned vnto you, and yee haue not wept.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And what? muſt wee then be ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, and ceaſe to ſpeake at all? or muſt wee, with the falſe Prophets, <note place="margin">Ezech. 13. 18.</note> ſpeake pleaſing things, ſowing Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes vnder mens arme-holes, and flattering them in their ſinnes? No, this is neyther good for vs, nor them: Not good for vs, ſaith <hi>Paul,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 9. 16.</note> there is a woe to vs, <hi>if wee preach not the Goſpell:</hi> not good for them, ſaith the Lord by <hi>Ieremiah, Their</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Iere. 6. 14.</note> 
               <hi>hurt is not healed with ſweet words.</hi> The calmeſt Sunne-ſhine doth leſſe purifie the aire, then the terribleſt thunder and lightning. The plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſanteſt Potion doth ſeldome purge ſo kindly as the bittereſt Pill. So words that to the care are ſweeteſt, are not alwayes to the heart the wholeſomeſt. And therefore <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſay</hi> muſt <hi>Cry aloud, and lift vp his</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Eſay 58. 1.</note> 
               <hi>voyce like a Trumpet. Ieremiah</hi> muſt <note place="margin">Iere. 1. 17.</note> 
               <hi>truſſe vp his loynes and not feare their</hi>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:18971:8"/>
               <hi>faces.</hi> Euery one of vs (that are the Surgeons of ſoules) had neede to cut and lance theſe feſtered ſores, and by ſharpe Corraſiues make them ſmart at the quicke, though our Patients be impatient, and our ſelues endure, with <hi>Moſes,</hi> murmu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring; <note place="margin">Exod. 5. 21.</note> with <hi>Michaiah,</hi> ſmiting; with <note place="margin">1 Kings 22. 24.</note> 
               <hi>Ieremiah,</hi> impriſoning; nay, vvith <note place="margin">Ierem. 32. 2.</note> 
               <hi>Iohn Baptiſt,</hi> beheading. <note place="margin">Marke 6. 27.</note>
            </p>
            <p>In which reſpects, and vpon <note place="margin">The Apologie for choiſe of the Text.</note> which conſiderations, (Right Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable, right Worſhipfull, and deare Brethren) when being called by commandement vnto this place, I meditated with my ſelfe what at this time to entreate of, as beſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitting the eſtate of our times, I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolued to decypher out ſome dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous wound, to lay open vnto you ſome capitall crime, ſome no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious impietie, ſome generall ſin, for which God may haue a iuſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouerſie with the Inhabitants of the Land: chooſing for this time &amp; in this place, to be (with <hi>Iames</hi> and
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:18971:8"/>
               <hi>Iohn) The ſonne of Thunder,</hi> rather <note place="margin">Marke 3. 17.</note> then (with <hi>Barnabas) the ſonne of Conſolation.</hi> Amongſt other the <note place="margin">Acts 4. 36.</note> ſinnes of our Land and crimes of our age, I finde, as none more hay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous, ſo none more common then the abuſe of Gods holy Name, by prophane Swearing. A ſinne moſt odious in the ſight of the immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall God, and yet ſo ſmall in the eyes of mortall men, that like a Leproſie <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Swearing,</hi> a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral ſinne, and ſpread ouer the vvhole Nation.</note> it hath ouer-ſpread the whole bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of our Nation, from the Cedar to the Shrub, from the higheſt to the loweſt, from the richeſt to the pooreſt, from the mightieſt to the meaneſt. And therefore giue mee leaue in this Honourable aſſembly plainely to entreat of theſe words I haue made choiſe of: and out of them to ſhew the haynouſneſſe of this ſinne, which in <hi>Ieremialas</hi> time cauſed the Land to mourne, for ſo faith our Prophes in this my Text.</p>
            <q>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:18971:9"/>
Becauſe of Oathes the Land mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth.</q>
            <p>NOt to ſtand eyther vpon the Author, or Occaſion, or Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexion, or Expoſition of this por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Scripture, which of it ſelfe is plaine and eaſie, but to come (without any Circumſtance) to the Text it ſelfe, it containeth (you ſee) <note place="margin">The Contents of the Text.</note> a complaint of the Prophet <hi>Iere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miah,</hi> laid in againſt the Iewes for not forſaking, and againſt their falſe Prophets, for not reprouing their vaine, idle, and wicked Swearing; whereby they both diſhonoured God, and cauſed his heauy Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to fall vpon them.</p>
            <p>In a word it ſheweth vnto vs the <note place="margin">The revvard of vnlavvfull Oathes.</note> reward of vnlawfull Oathes, which is firſt (as you may conſider it) ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply propounded, <hi>Mourning:</hi> and <note place="margin">1</note> then aggrauated by the generalitie <note place="margin">2</note> of it, in that it extendeth to the whole <hi>Land,</hi> ſo ſaith the Prophet,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:18971:9"/>
               <hi>The Land mourneth.</hi> In the firſt, we are to note two things; firſt, the <note place="margin">The parts.</note> cauſe: ſecondly, the effect.</p>
            <list>
               <item>The cauſe, <hi>Swearing.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1</note>
               </item>
               <item>The effect, <hi>Mourning.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">2</note>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>The cauſe, in the former words, <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of Oathes:</hi> the effect, in the next, <hi>the Land mourneth.</hi> And well may Oathes cauſe mourning, and ſwearing end in ſorrowing. For as to thoſe that doe now mourne in <hi>Sion,</hi> there is a bleſſing pronounced, <note place="margin">Matth. 5. 4.</note> and comfort promiſed, <hi>They ſhall</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 61. 3.</note> 
               <hi>haue beautie for aſhes, ioy for mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and the garment of gladneſſe for the ſpirit of heauineſſe;</hi> their <hi>Aprill</hi> ſhowers bring <hi>May</hi> flowers, <hi>they that</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 126. 5.</note> 
               <hi>ſow in teares ſhall reape in ioy.</hi> So to thoſe, that heere paſſe their time in iollitie, and neuer thinke vpon the affliction of <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> but make Oaths their paſtime, and ſwearing their muſicke in their greateſt merriment, there is a woe denounced and iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment threatned, <hi>their laughing ſhall</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Luke 6. 25.</note> 
               <hi>end</hi> (ſaith Chriſt) <hi>in wailing and</hi>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:18971:10"/>
               <hi>weeping:</hi> their Oathes, ſaith my Text, ſhall conclude in mourning.</p>
            <q>Becauſe of Oathes the Land mourneth. <note place="margin">Text.</note>
            </q>
            <p>FIrſt, of the cauſe, and then of the <note place="margin">The firſt part.</note> effect. The cauſe is expreſſed in the firſt words, <hi>Becauſe of Oathes.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">The cauſe.</note> I know indeed, the Hebrew word here vſed, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, is diuerſly read of Interpreters vpon this place. But I take our common tranſlation to be the moſt proper, and therefore read it: not, becauſe of curſing, as <hi>Hierome</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>A facie maledi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctionis.</hi> Hieron. <hi>Propter execra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionem.</hi> Treme. <hi>Arbitrer notari hic periur.</hi> Cal. <hi>Propter iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ramentum fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum.</hi> Chal. Paraph.</note> and <hi>Tremellius:</hi> nor, becauſe of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iurie, as <hi>Caluin</hi> and the <hi>Chaldee</hi> Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raphraſe; but becauſe of Swearing, as our late tranſlation; or, becauſe of Oathes, as our <hi>Geneua</hi> readeth it. Which notwithſtanding wee muſt not with the Anabaptiſts take to be vnderſtood of all kinde of Swearing whatſoeuer, but onely of vaine Oathes, and no other. For an Oath <note place="margin">An Oath in it ſelfe good, but may be abuſed, as Prayer.</note> in it ſelfe is good, and warranted by God, but yet may be abuſed as euery
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:18971:10"/>
other good thing. Praier which is an excellent part of Gods Seruice, is di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſly vſed and performed: Some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time well, and then it is acceptable: ſometime ill, and then abhomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. In like manner an Oath, which is a kinde of Prayer, is in ſome caſes lawfull, in other vnlawfull. Lawfull it is when rightly vſed: vnlawfull it is when Gods worſhip is abuſed: For the better explaining whereof I ſhall thinke it not amiſſe to inſiſt vpon theſe two things. Firſt, that there is <note place="margin">1</note> a lawfull vſe of Oathes. Secondly, what Oathes are lawfull, what vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull. <note place="margin">2</note>
            </p>
            <p>For the firſt. That there is a <note place="margin">1 That there is a lavvfull vſe of Oathes, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth, 1 by precept.</note> lawfull vſe of Oathes, it may appeare both by precept and by patterne. Firſt, by precept from the Lord himſelfe, as <hi>Deut.</hi> 6. 13. <hi>Thou ſhalt feare the Lord thy GOD, and ſerue him, and ſhalt ſweare by his Name.</hi> So, <hi>Thou ſhalt ſweare the Lord li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth, &amp;c. Ierem.</hi> 4. 2. And he doth not onely command it, but promiſe
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:18971:11"/>
to reward it, <hi>Ierem.</hi> 12. 16. The end <note place="margin">Ier. 12. 16.</note> why an Oath is thus ordained and <note place="margin">The end of ordaining an Oath.</note> required, is two-fold:
<list>
                  <item>1 <hi>The glory of God.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2 <hi>The good of Man.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
And firſt, it maketh much for <hi>the glory of God,</hi> when hereby he is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pealed vnto, <note place="margin">1 The glory of God.</note> as the chiefe Iudge of the whole World, and men flee to his Name, as to <hi>a ſtrong Tower, Prouerb.</hi> 18. 10. In this regard ſaith <note place="margin">Prou 10. 18.</note> one, an Oath is a diuine thing; for it <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Diuina res eſt iuſiurandum: ſacra enim an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chora eſt, ad qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> confugitur, quum humana ſapie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tia progredi non po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt.</hi> Huld. Zvvin. Elench. in Catabap. Strophas.</note> is a holy Anchor-hold, to which we flee when mans wiſdome can goe no further.</p>
            <p>And ſurely herein wee giue vnto God, firſt, <hi>the glory of omniſcience,</hi> when wee call him to teſtifie of our ſecret thoughts, and ſo acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge him <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <note n="*" place="margin">Acts 1. 14.</note> 
               <hi>The knower of hearts.</hi> Secondly, <hi>the glory of Truth,</hi> when he is appealed vnto, as Truths witneſſe and maintainer, and falſhoods reuenger. Thirdly, <hi>the glory of Power,</hi> whereby hee
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:18971:11"/>
can; and <hi>of Iuſtice,</hi> whereby he will take vengeance of thoſe that ſweare <note place="margin">Muſcul. <hi>append. ad Pſal</hi> 15. <hi>de</hi> Iuramen. <hi>Quare plane inſani ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minis eſſe opor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tet, ſi quis iura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menti vſum, modo leuit as &amp; mendacium ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, non agno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerit tam non derogare quic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam gloriae Dei, vt illam etiam illuſtret.</hi>
               </note> falſely. Wherefore in theſe reſpects we may conclude with <hi>Muſculus, that certainly he can be iudged no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then a madman, who will not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge that the vſe of an oath, being taken neither lightly nor falſly; is ſo far from any whit derogating from the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of God, that it doth euen much ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt, and ſet it forth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note n="*" place="margin">2 The good of man.</note> The ſecond end why an Oath is of neceſſitie required, is <hi>the good of Man,</hi> it being (as <hi>Melancthon</hi> calleth it) <note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Praecipuum vinculum ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis politici,</hi> Phil. Melanct: in Mat 5.</note> 
               <hi>the chiefe bond of ciuil order:</hi> for hereby is <note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>Propter iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam conſeruan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam, veritatem aſtruandam, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>micitiam confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandam; &amp;c.</hi> Bonaueh. cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiloq. pars 1. cap. 12.</note> Right and Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice maintained, Truth and Verity preſerued, Peace and concord eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed, diſcord &amp; diſſention ended: There muſt be an end of ſtrife, who doth not grant it? An end of ſtrife there cannot be, till confirmation on the one ſide be ſtronger then on the other. To this end in the firſt place reaſons muſt be vſed: when theſe faile, then by witneſſes muſt
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:18971:12"/>
the matter be ſtabliſhed: when wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes faile, an Oath muſt be vſed: <note place="margin">Deut. 19. 15.</note> and this is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the end of ſtrife, as the Apoſtle calleth it: <hi>An Oath for confirmation is the end of all ſtrife, Heb.</hi> 6. 16. So we ſee that an Oath is ordained by God, and that to very good end and purpoſe.</p>
            <p>Now ſecondly, as wee haue pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept to command it, ſo patterne to <note place="margin">2 By patterne.</note> commend it. It is commended by example and patterne without ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception; and that,</p>
            <p>Firſt, of the Saints of GOD.</p>
            <p>Secondly, of the Angels of GOD.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, of GOD himſelfe.</p>
            <p>Firſt of the Saints of God, both in the Old Teſtament and New. In the <note place="margin">1 Of the Saints of God.</note> Old Teſtament, of <hi>Abraham</hi> to the King of <hi>Sodom, Gen.</hi> 21. of <hi>Iacob</hi> to his Vncle <hi>Laban, Gen.</hi> 31. of <hi>Ioſeph</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Gen. 21. 24.</note> to his Father <hi>Iacob, Gen.</hi> 47. So of <note place="margin">Gen. 31. 53.</note> 
               <hi>Dauid</hi> to <hi>Ionathan,</hi> of <hi>Elias</hi> to <hi>Oba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diah,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Gen. 47. 31.</note> 
               <note place="margin">1 Sam 20.</note> of <hi>Eliſha</hi> to <hi>Iehoram,</hi> and diuers others. And from the Old <note place="margin">1 King. 18. 15.</note> 
               <note place="margin">2 King. 3. 14.</note> Teſtament come wee to the New,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:18971:12"/>
               <hi>Paul</hi> doth it in diuers Epiſtles; as to the <hi>Romanes, God is my witneſſe, Rom.</hi> 1. 9. To the <hi>Corinthians, I call</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Rom. 1. 9.</note> 
               <hi>God for a record vnto my ſoule,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. 23. <note place="margin">2 Cor. 1. 23.</note> To the <hi>Galathians, I witneſſe before God that I lye not, Gal.</hi> 1. 20. <note place="margin">Gal. 1. 20.</note> To the <hi>Philippians, God is my re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord, Phil.</hi> 1. 8. Thus wee haue the <note place="margin">Phil. 1. 8.</note> patterne of the holy men of God.</p>
            <p>Secondly, not onely ſo, but of <note place="margin">2 Of the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels of God.</note> the Angels of GOD. So wee read, <hi>Dan.</hi> 12. 7. that the Angell held vp both his hands, and <hi>ſware by him</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Dan. 12. 7.</note> 
               <hi>that liueth for euer:</hi> ſo we read, <hi>Rene.</hi> 10. 5. 6. <hi>The Angell life vp his</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Reuel. 10. 5. 6.</note> 
               <hi>hand to Heauen, and ſwore by him that liueth for euermore.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly and laſtly, of God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, the patterne of patternes. He <note place="margin">3 Of God himſelfe.</note> is recorded in Scripture to haue ſworne diuers Oathes: ſometime <hi>by his holineſſe, Pſal.</hi> 89. ſometime <hi>by his right hand, Eſa.</hi> 62. ſometime <hi>by</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 89. 35.</note> 
               <hi>his great Name, Ierem.</hi> 44. ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time <note place="margin">Iſa. 62. 8.</note> 
               <hi>by his ſoule, Ier.</hi> 51. Not that <note place="margin">Ier. 44. 26.</note> his ſaying needed confirming, <note place="margin">Ier. 51. 14.</note>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:18971:13"/>
whoſe bare word is <hi>Yea</hi> and <hi>Amen:</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 1. 20. <hi>Propter homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num ſocordiam Deus iurat.</hi> Cal.</note> but to conuince the infirmitie of our nature, and to comfort it being con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uicted. He hath done it, as the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle ſaith, <hi>(ex àbundanti)</hi> willingly <note place="margin">prael. in Ier. <hi>Cur Scriptura iurantem indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cit Deum, nimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum vt infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatem naturae noſtrae coargue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret, &amp; conuicta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> conſolaretur.</hi> Philo. in libel. de ſacrif. <hi>Cain</hi> &amp; <hi>Abel.</hi>
               </note> more abundantly to ſhew the ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleneſſe of his counſell, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6. 17. For this cauſe he ſwore to <hi>Abraham</hi> euer to bleſſe him, <hi>Gene.</hi> 22. 16. to <hi>Dauid</hi> neuer to forſake him, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 132. 11. to the Gentiles not to be angry with them, <hi>Eſa.</hi> 54. 8. Thus by all that hath beene ſaid, it is eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent that there is a lawfull vſe of Oathes, which God hath not onely <note place="margin">2 What Oaths are lavvfull, vvhat vnlavv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full.</note> by precept inioyned, but alſo by his owne practiſe approued. Now it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maineth that I come to ſhew vvhat Oathes are lawfull, what vnlawfull.</p>
            <p>For the firſt: A lawfull Oath, I call <note place="margin">1 The deſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a lavv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Oath.</note> that when wee ſweare in a waighty matter, by IEHOVAH, in truth, in righteouſneſſe, and in iudgement. Of theſe things in order.</p>
            <p>And firſt, <hi>it muſt be in a wàightie</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 It muſt be onely in a vvaighty mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</note> 
               <hi>matter,</hi> when all proofes and teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:18971:13"/>
faile, and when the contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſie cannot be decided, nor the truth diſcerned, nor the matter de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined, but onely by <hi>Iehouah;</hi> for <note place="margin">Reaſon.</note> then onely it maketh for the glory of God, when he is appealed vnto in a matter of moment &amp; importance, and ſo acknowledged all-ſeeing and all-powerfull: and on the contrary the name of God is much diſhono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, when called to witneſſe in euery trifle which is not worth an Oath. <note place="margin">Plaine by a ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militude.</note> It were (we know) a diſgrace, and ſo it would be taken to diſturbe and diſquiet the Kings Maieſtie vvith ſuch a cauſe, as the loweſt and baſeſt Officer might determine. How then can God take it, to be made ſo bolde with, as to be called out of his Throne in Heauen to decide trifles? It is to make leſſe reckoning of him <note place="margin">Guiliel. Tripolit.</note> then the <hi>Turkes</hi> of their <hi>Mahomet,</hi> by whom they will not ſweare light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and vainely, but vpon occaſion of great neceſſitie.</p>
            <p>Secondly, it muſt be by <hi>Iehouah</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 It muſt be by <hi>Iehouah.</hi>
               </note>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:18971:14"/>
as is plaine by the Word of God, and reaſon.</p>
            <p>Firſt, by the word of God, <hi>Thou ſhalt ſweare by his Name, Deut.</hi> 10. 20. <hi>Euery tongue ſhall ſweare by me,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Deut. 10. 20.</note> 
               <hi>Eſai.</hi> 45. 23. <hi>And he that ſweareth</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 45. 23.</note> 
               <hi>in the Earth, ſhall ſweare by the true God, Eſai.</hi> 65. 16. <note place="margin">Iſa. 65. 16.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, by reaſon: for firſt, to him we ſweare by, we giue diuine <note place="margin">Reaſon.</note> honour, and attribute omniſcience, <note place="margin">1 Hee onely is omniſcient.</note> and the diſcerning of thoughts: for an Oath is taken in vncertaine, and vnknowne matters, of which hee onely can iudge that knoweth the heart. Now this is proper to God alone, <hi>hee diſcouereth the deepe and ſecret things, Dan.</hi> 2. 22. <hi>and he know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the hearts of all the children of</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Dan. 2. 22.</note> 
               <hi>men,</hi> 1 <hi>Kin.</hi> 8. 39. Therefore he one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to be ſworne by. <note place="margin">1 King. 8. 39.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, to him we ſweare by, <note place="margin">2 He onely is omnipotent.</note> we attribute omnipotence, and the reuenging of falſhood. This alſo is proper to God; therefore he onely <note place="margin">Mihi vindicta.</note> to be ſworne by, for <hi>vengeance is</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Deut. 32. 35.</note>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:18971:14"/>
               <hi>mine,</hi> ſaith the Lord, <hi>Rom.</hi> 12. 19. <note place="margin">Rom 12. 19.</note> and <hi>he is able to deſtroy body and ſoule in hell fire, Matth.</hi> 10. 28. <note place="margin">Matth. 10. 28.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, God onely is to be inuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated, <note place="margin">3 Hee onely to be inuocated.</note> and prayed vnto. Now an Oath is a kinde of inuocation, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in wee deſire God to vvitneſſe the truth of our ſpeech, and to puniſh vs if wee ſpeake falſely. Therefore we are to ſweare neither by Angell, Saint, nor any other creature, but by God alone.</p>
            <p>All theſe are his royal Titles, and <note place="margin">Not the leaſt of theſe Titles muſt be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied him.</note> not the leaſt of them muſt be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied him. He is not as the Gods of the Heathen, which (like good fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes) would part ſtakes: but the true God is a <hi>iealous God,</hi> &amp; <hi>will not giue his glory to another, Eſa.</hi> 48. 11. <note place="margin">Exod. 24. 5.</note> Hence aroſe the vſe which was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong <note place="margin">Eſa. 48. 11.</note> the Iewes, (and is obſerued <note place="margin">Gloriam meam non dabo alteri.</note> in theſe our times in the taking of publike Oaths) to touch the Bible, when we ſweare not by it, but the contents of it, which is God, and the ſumme of it, which is Chriſt, vvho
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:18971:15"/>
becauſe hee is the ſubiect of the vvhole Word, is therefore called <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Iohn 1. 1.</note> 
               <hi>the Word, Iohn</hi> 1. 1. And ſo much for the ſecond condition of a law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Oath.</p>
            <p>To proceed: as it muſt be in a <note place="margin">3 It muſt be in <hi>veritate.</hi>
               </note> waightie matter, and by <hi>Iehouah,</hi> ſo in <hi>Truth,</hi> in <hi>Righteouſneſſe,</hi> and in <hi>Iudgement.</hi> Which three laſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perties are ſet downe by our Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, <note place="margin">D. Hieron. in Ierem. <hi>Tres comites iura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menti, ſine qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus non iura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentum, ſed periurium fiat.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Chap.</hi> 4. 2. and they are tear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by a Father, the three Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions of an Oath; without which it becommeth no Oath, but periurie. We muſt ſweare,
<list>
                  <item>1 <hi>In Truth; not falſely.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2 <hi>In Righteouſnes; not wickedly.</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Iudicio caret iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ramentumincau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum: veritate iuramentum mendax: iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia iuramentum iniquum &amp; illi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citum.</hi> Aquin.</note>
                  </item>
                  <item>3 <hi>In Iudgement; not raſhly.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
By the firſt are condemned falſe and fraudulent Oathes: by the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, ſinfull and vnlawfull Oathes: by the third, raſh and vnaduiſed Oathes. To ſpeake of them in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der: And firſt, that an Oath muſt be <hi>in Truth,</hi> is a knowne truth, and needeth no proofe; you ſee the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:18971:15"/>
God of Truth requireth it. Now, <note place="margin">An Oath tvvo-fold.</note> vvhereas an Oath is two-fold, either <hi>Aſſertorie,</hi> or <hi>Promiſſory:</hi> by the <note place="margin">Aſſertorium de facto: promiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſorium de fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turo.</note> one affirming ſomething done; by the other, promiſing ſomething to be done; we are to know that in both <note place="margin">Truth neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie in both.</note> Truth is neceſſary.</p>
            <p>And firſt, in a <hi>Promiſſory</hi> Oath we <note place="margin">1 In an Oath <hi>promiſſorie.</hi>
               </note> are commanded firſt to ſweare what vvee meane to performe, and after <note place="margin">1</note> to performe vvhat we haue ſworne. <note place="margin">2</note> Not <hi>breaking our promiſe, Numb.</hi> 30. 3. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deus dicitur iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raſſe ſermone Metaphorico</hi> 1. <hi>quoad ſimilitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinem iurantis immobiliter ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid delibera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uit, per quod de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claratur, non ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum quae promit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuntur Deum decreuiſſe, ſed omnimoda im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mobilitate defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ſſe.</hi> Caietan. in Cap 2. Gen.</note> but <hi>performing our Oathes, Mat.</hi> 5. 33. And for this we haue the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of God himſelfe; he <hi>remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>breth the Oath to Abraham, Lu.</hi> 1. 37. So muſt wee, if the ſonnes of God, and ſuch as will reſt in his holy Mountaine, not change our Oath, though to our hinderance, <hi>Pſa.</hi> 15. 4. Nay, <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Cic. offi. lib.</hi> 3.</note> 
               <hi>Tully</hi> the Heathen Oratour telleth vs, that an Oath muſt be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>credly kept toward our enemies: as <hi>Dauid</hi> made conſcience of keeping his Oath to <hi>Shimei,</hi> that before had curſed him, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 19. 23. And
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:18971:16"/>
therefore the Latine vvord <hi>(Iura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentum,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Valla. <hi>lib.</hi> 6. <hi>eleg. cap.</hi> 37. <hi>quae enim iuramus firma et immota debent eſſe.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>à iure manente)</hi> plainely ſignifieth vnto vs, that our Oathes muſt be ſtedfaſt and conſtant. And ſo much the Greeke word impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth vnto vs (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) whether wee <note place="margin">Ioan. Scap. <hi>ex Euſt. pag.</hi> 1194.</note> vnderſtand it, <hi>(quaſi</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) a <hi>hedge,</hi> or <hi>(quaſi</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) a <hi>bound,</hi> or limit: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Swearer hath hedged himſelfe about with Gods truth, and is ſo brought within bounds and limits, that hee cannot but per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme what hee hath ſworne. And ſo much for truth in an <hi>Oath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſorie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, in an Oath <hi>aſſertorie</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 In an Oath Aſſertorie a tvvo-fold truth.</note> there is a double truth required: <hi>Logicall,</hi> and <hi>Morall,</hi> as the Schoole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men ſpeak. The one, the truth of the thing: the other, the truth of the minde. The firſt, vvhen vve ſpeake as it is: the ſecond, when we thinke as we ſpeake. In a lawfull Oath both are requiſite. Firſt, that our tongue <note place="margin">1 <hi>Veritas Logica.</hi>
               </note> goe according to the thing, and that not vpon Coniectures, and
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:18971:16"/>
probabilities, but vpon a truth, and a truth vndoubted, for which wee haue good ground, proofe, and warrant. Secondly, that our minde accord with our tongue: not mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning <note place="margin">2 <hi>Veritas mora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis.</hi>
               </note> one thing, when wee ſweare another, but according to the ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple and plaine vnderſtanding of the Oath, being in conſcience per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded of the truth of it. Thus in euery particular it ſtandeth vs in hand to haue <hi>our laynes girt about with veritie, Epheſ.</hi> 6. 14. and good <note place="margin">Epheſ. 6. 14. Reaſon.</note> reaſon: for otherwiſe wee eyther make God a lyer, or elſe eaſie to be deceiued, when wee call him to wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe a falſhood: both which are impious, and very iniurious, both to God our Creator, who is <hi>The God</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1</note> 
               <hi>of truth, Pſal.</hi> 31. 5. and to Chriſt <note place="margin">Pſal. 31. 5.</note> our Redeemer; who is <hi>Truth it ſelfe,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2</note> 
               <hi>Iohn</hi> 14. 6. and to the holy Ghoſt <note place="margin">Iohn 14. 6.</note> our Sanctifier, who is <hi>the Spirit of Truth, Iohn</hi> 14. 26. And ſo much <note place="margin">3</note> for the third condition of a lawfull <note place="margin">Iohn 14. 26.</note> Oath.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:18971:17"/>
Fourthly, it muſt be in <hi>Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe</hi> 
               <note place="margin">4 It muſt be, <hi>in Iuſticia.</hi>
               </note> according to Iuſtice. And here wee muſt chiefely looke to two things:<list>
                  <item>1. <hi>That the Occaſion</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. <hi>That the Matter</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <hi>be iuſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, that there be <hi>iuſt cauſe and</hi> 
               <note place="margin">And here vvee muſt looke to tvvo things:</note> 
               <hi>occaſion</hi> to take an Oath, eyther in reſpect of <hi>God,</hi> or <hi>Man.</hi> Firſt, <hi>in reſpect of God,</hi> when thereby his do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine <note place="margin">1 That there be iuſt cauſe and occaſion to take an Oath, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect:</note> is confirmed, his honour ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uanced, his ſeruice furthered: thus <hi>Dauid ſwore</hi> to binde himſelfe to his worſhip. <hi>I haue ſworne and will performe it, Pſal.</hi> 119. 106. thus <note place="margin">1 Of God. Pſal. 119. 106. 2 Chron. 15. 14</note> did <hi>Aſa</hi> and his people, 2 <hi>Chro.</hi> 15. thus <hi>Ioſiah</hi> &amp; his people, 2 <hi>Chro.</hi> 34. <note place="margin">2 Chron. 34 31</note> Secondly, <hi>in reſpect of Man,</hi> when <note place="margin">Nehem. 10. 29</note> thereby eyther publikely or pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uately, <note place="margin">2 Of Man. Exod. 22. 10 11</note> neceſſary Leagues and Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenants <note place="margin">1</note> are confirmed; homage <note place="margin">2</note> and Allegiance to Princes teſtified; the life, goods, or good name ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of our ſelues, or our neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour <note place="margin">3</note> preſerued, the truth in doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full matters diſcerned; and in a <note place="margin">4</note>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:18971:17"/>
word, brotherly loue furthered. <note place="margin">5</note>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, as the <hi>occaſion,</hi> ſo the <hi>Matter</hi> it ſelfe muſt be <hi>iuſt</hi> and <hi>law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full:</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 That the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter it ſelfe be iuſt and lavvful.</note> not onely true for ſubſtance, but righteous: which is then, when it doth ſtand with Pietie and Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie. And reaſon there is it ſhould <note place="margin">Reaſon.</note> doe ſo; for wee muſt ſweare accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the rule of godlineſſe: God will be worſhipped with his owne worſhip, and hee will not be a wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of his owne diſhonour, and of harming our neighbour. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hee that ſweareth to doe a <note place="margin">He that ſvvea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth a thing vniuſt, maketh God, eyther the vvitneſſe of a lie, or an ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prouer of ſinne.</note> thing vniuſt, eyther ſweareth not as he meaneth to doe, and ſo maketh God <hi>the witneſſe of a Lie:</hi> or elſe ſweareth with reſolution, and ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth God <hi>an approuer of Sinne:</hi> both wayes contemning his power, as though he were vnable to reuenge. And ſo much for the fourth condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a lawfull Oath.</p>
            <p>The fiſt and laſt followeth; it muſt be <hi>in Iudgement.</hi> Now, that is <note place="margin">5 It muſt be, <hi>in Iudicio.</hi>
               </note> an Oath <hi>in Iudgement</hi> (vvhether
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:18971:18"/>
publike or priuate) which is done with vnderſtanding of the Law of <note place="margin">An Oath in iudgement. vvhat.</note> God, and of the Country wherein wee liue, therewith concurring. <hi>Iudgement</hi> then requireth Diſcreti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Perk.</hi> Caſ. of Conſc. <hi>Lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 13. <hi>ſect.</hi> 2. <hi>quaeſt.</hi> 2.</note> Vnderſtanding, Conſideration; and that of fiue things principally: Firſt, of the thing in queſtion, which is to be confirmed: Secondly, of <note place="margin">1</note> the nature of the Oath that is taken: <note place="margin">2</note> Thirdly, of the minde and true mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning <note place="margin">3</note> of him that ſweareth: Fourth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <note place="margin">4</note> of the particular circumſtances, of time, place, and perſons, when, where, and before whom hee ſwea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth: Laſtly, of the euent and iſſue of the Oath. All theſe are duely to <note place="margin">5</note> be regarded. The reaſon is, becauſe <note place="margin">Reaſon.</note> God is the God of order, and in matter of truth and righteouſneſſe will haue all things done according to the rule of Policie and Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. And ſurely this <hi>Iudgement</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Iudgement of great vſe in an Oath:</note> and vnderſtanding is of great vſe in an Oath: for, it will guide vs to take it, neuer but vpon ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitie,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:18971:18"/>
and then aduiſedly.</p>
            <p>Firſt, onely <hi>vpon neceſſary occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion:</hi> 
               <note place="margin">For it vvil cauſe vs to take it, 1 Onely vpon neceſſarie oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion.</note> and ſo much is implyed in the Hebrew word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which (being vſed in the <hi>Paſſiue)</hi> ſignifieth to be ſworne, rather then to ſweare: to ſhew, that wee are to doe it ſparing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, being drawne thereunto by ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitie. For, an Oath being a ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie good, is not good, but when <note place="margin">Bonum neceſſariu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> extra terminos neceſſitatis non eſt bonum.</note> it is neceſſary: as a Potion not good, but in time of ſickneſſe.</p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>when neceſſarie to doe it aduiſedly:</hi> not raſhly, but diſcreet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <note place="margin">2 When neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary, to doe it aduiſedly.</note> with due deliberation, with reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, and feare of ſo glorious a Maieſtie. It is the precept of an Heathen man, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>reuerence an Oath:</hi> and the Childe of God <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Venerare Iura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> Pytha.</note> is deſcribed <hi>to feare an Oath, Eccleſ.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Eccleſ. 9. 2.</note> 9. 2. whence wee read that <hi>the Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raelites ſwore with all their hearts,</hi> 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 15. 15. that is, all their vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, all their affections, all <note place="margin">2 Chron. 15. 15</note> the powers of their minde were em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed, and ſet on worke, in a due
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:18971:19"/>
conſideration, and reuerent feare of the Oath and Couenant made vnto the Lord. And ſo much for the laſt condition of a lawfull Oath.</p>
            <p>Now from Oaths lawfull I come <note place="margin">2</note> vnto vnlawfull, which what they are will appeare from that which hath beene ſaid, being ſuch as faile in the former rules. An <hi>vnlawfull</hi> 
               <note place="margin">The deſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lavvful. Oath.</note> 
               <hi>Oath</hi> therefore I call that: when we ſweare in a matter whether waightie or light vpon euery little occaſion, or by any other thing then God, or not <hi>in truth, righteouſneſſe, and iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment:</hi> of which in order.</p>
            <p>And firſt, it is <hi>vnlawfull</hi> in a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <note place="margin">1 Vnlavvfull vvhen vpon e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery little oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion.</note> waightie or light, when vpon <hi>euery little occaſion.</hi> Wee reade of <hi>Moſes, Exod.</hi> 18. that hee had in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriour officers to iudge the ſmaller <note place="margin">Exod. 18. 26.</note> cauſes, and the people came not to him, but vpon ſome great occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, when the cauſes were difficult and hard to be decided. How much <note place="margin">It is much to debaſe God.</note> then is the ſupreame Iudge of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen and earth debaſed, when called
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:18971:19"/>
from heauen to giue iudgement vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſmall or no occaſion? It is to <note place="margin">And to ſet leſſe by him, then by an earthly Iudge:</note> ſet leſſe by him then by an earthly <hi>Iudge,</hi> whom we count it a diſgrace to trouble in a trifle. Nay, it is to deale worſe by him then by a good <note place="margin">Nay, then by a good ſuite of apparrell.</note> ſuite of apparrell, vvhich vvee vvill not vveare euery day, but lay it vp for ſpeciall dayes: And yet the Name of God, how is it vvorne and torne, euery day of the vveeke, eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry houre of the day, (I had almoſt ſaid) euery minute of the houre. <note n="*" place="margin">Luke. 23. 34.</note> 
               <hi>Oh Father forgiue them: for they know not what they doe.</hi> They know not vvhat it is to ſweare. For what is an Oath? not onely (as <note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iuramentum eſt cum diuina vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratione dictio probationis ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers.</hi> Ariſt. Rhet.</note> 
               <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> defineth it) <hi>Aſaying voide of proofe, with diuine worſhip:</hi> nor onely (as <note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iurare nihil aliud eſt, quam Deum teſtem in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uccare.</hi> Aquin.</note> 
               <hi>Aquinas) A calling of God to wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe:</hi> (and yet if it were no more, it were not to be taken idly) but an Oath properly, <note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iuramentum eſt inuocatio Dei, qua petitur, vt is tanquam vnicus cordu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s inſpector, teſtimonium det veritati, &amp; iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantem puniat, ſi ſciens fallat.</hi> Vrſinus Catec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pars 3. quaeſt. 102.</note> 
               <hi>Is a ſolemne inuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of the holy Name of God, whereby we deſire him, as being the onely ſeer of hearts, to witneſſe the</hi>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:18971:20"/>
               <hi>truth of our ſpeech, and to puniſh vs, if wee ſpeake falſely.</hi> And yet as though God vvere vnworthy to haue reuerence, or vnable to take vengeance, how doe men pollute his Name by daily and hourely Oathes, vvherby they turne <hi>(Aſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum in domum communem)</hi> the San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuarie of Veritie into a common houſe of vanitie. So vve ſee in the firſt place Oathes are <hi>vnlawfull,</hi> vvhen taken vpon <hi>euery little occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>vnlawfull,</hi> when not <note place="margin">2 Vnlavvfull, vvhen by any other thing then God, be it eyther <hi>pro eo,</hi> or <hi>cum eo.</hi>
               </note> by <hi>Iehouah.</hi> And here men offend againſt God two wayes: firſt, when they leaue his <hi>Name,</hi> and take ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>for it:</hi> ſecondly, vvhen they vſe it, but adde another <hi>with it:</hi> both are forbidden <hi>by God:</hi> both are <note place="margin">1</note> threatned <hi>of God.</hi> The firſt, <hi>Iere.</hi> 5. 7. <note place="margin">Ierem. 5. 7.</note> 
               <hi>How ſhould I ſpare thee for this? thy</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Amos. 8. 14.</note> 
               <hi>children haue forſaken me, and ſworne by them that are no Gods.</hi> The ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, <note place="margin">2</note> 
               <hi>Zeph.</hi> 1. 5. where hee threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth <note place="margin">Zeph. 1. 5.</note> to cut off thoſe, that <hi>ſweare</hi>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:18971:20"/>
               <hi>by the Lord, and ſweare by Mal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cham.</hi> Hence then come to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proued <note place="margin">Hence are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proued diuers kindes of Oathes.</note> diuers kindes of <hi>Oathes,</hi> chiefely theſe:
<list>
                  <item>1. <hi>Heatheniſh.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. <hi>Ciuill.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. <hi>Superſticious.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>4. <hi>Impious.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>5. <hi>Ridiculous.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
Firſt, all <hi>Heatheniſh Oathes:</hi> by their <note place="margin">1 All Heathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh Oathes by their Gods. Gen. 31. 53.</note> 
               <hi>Gods,</hi> as <hi>Laban,</hi> by the God of <hi>Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rah,</hi> an Idolater, <hi>Gen.</hi> 31. 53. and as <hi>Iezabel</hi> by her <hi>Gods,</hi> 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 19. 2. Theſe Oathes are expreſſely forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den by God himſelfe, <hi>Exod.</hi> 23. 13. <note place="margin">Exod. 23. 13.</note> 
               <hi>Yee ſhall make no mention of the name</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ioſh. 23. 7.</note> 
               <hi>of other Gods, neyther ſhall it be</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 16. 4.</note> 
               <hi>heard out of thy mouth.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Hoſ. 2. 17.</note>
            </p>
            <p>The ſecond kinde here reproued, <note place="margin">Zach. 13. 2.</note> are <hi>Ciuill Oathes.</hi> Giue me leaue ſo <note place="margin">2 All Ciuill Oathes, by the Creatures.</note> to tearme them for diſtinction ſake, becauſe among carnall men they paſſe vvithout controulement, as readily and freely, as <hi>ciuill</hi> ſpeech from their mouthes. As, how com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon a thing is it, among the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faner
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:18971:21"/>
ſort, to ſweare by the <hi>light, Heauen, Sunne, fire, meate, drinke, mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie:</hi> ſo, by their <hi>hand, ſoule,</hi> and ſuch like: by which kinde of Oathes they are very <hi>iniurious</hi> both to <hi>God</hi> 
               <note place="margin">By vvhich Oathes they are 1 <hi>iniurious</hi> to God.</note> and to <hi>themſelues.</hi> Firſt, <hi>iniurious to God,</hi> in that they inuocate the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, vvhich is onely proper to the creator: and ſo they place them <note place="margin">Iurare eſt ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid dicere cum inuocatione Dei Ergo non iuran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum per creatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ras quia non ſunt inuocandae.</note> in the ſeate of God, making them corriuals vvith the <hi>Monarch</hi> of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen and earth, and matching them with him in greatneſſe, both of Wiſedome to know ſecrets, and of Power to reuenge falſehood, both <note place="margin">Melancth. in</note> vvhich GOD requireth as due to <note place="margin">Mat. 5. 34.</note> himſelfe alone. <note place="margin">Iſa. 48. 11.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>iniurious to themſelues,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 <hi>Iniurious</hi> to themſelues.</note> calling thoſe things to <hi>iudge</hi> them, vvhich God hath made to <hi>ſerue them.</hi> And ſurely, it is worth the <note place="margin">They much diſgrace them ſelues.</note> marking and obſeruing how a num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber (that in other caſes ſtand vpon their credit) doe heerein much diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace themſelues, ſetting thoſe things as <hi>Lords aboue them,</hi> that are
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:18971:21"/>
as <hi>ſeruants ſubiect to them;</hi> for men <note place="margin">Pſal. 8. 6.</note> ſweare by him that is greater then themſelues. <hi>Heb.</hi> 6. 16. <note place="margin">Heb. 6. 16.</note>
            </p>
            <p>The third kinde here reproued <note place="margin">3 All ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious Oathes, by Saints, or Idols.</note> are <hi>ſuperſtitious Oathes,</hi> that ſauour of ſuperſtition, and nothing elſe. Such are the Oathes of the <hi>Popiſh</hi> ſort by their <hi>Idols,</hi> as <hi>Maſſe, Rood, Croſſe, Chriſtendom, Teſtament, Euan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geliſts:</hi> So <hi>by our Lady,</hi> by the <hi>Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine Mary,</hi> and other <hi>Saints.</hi> By which kinde of <hi>Oathes</hi> they ſhew <note place="margin">By the vſe of vvhich Oathes is ſhevved 1 Great folly. 2 Groſſe Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrie.</note> both <hi>great folly</hi> and <hi>groſſe Idolatrie.</hi> Their <hi>folly,</hi> in calling them to wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, vvho can neither heare them, nor helpe them. Their <hi>Idolatry,</hi> in forſaking the true God, and making creatures their God. For, when a man ſweareth by any other thing then GOD, hee maketh that his <note place="margin">Chryſt. Hom. 12 oper. imper. ſuper Matth. <hi>Idolatriam ab eo committi dicit, qui iurat per ali quid. quod Deus non eſt, eo quod illud deifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cet per quod iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat.</hi>
               </note> God, and himſelfe an Idolater, as <hi>Ierome</hi> and <hi>Chriſoſtome</hi> vpon the fift of <hi>Matthew</hi> doe both affirme: therefore we may conclude, that in an Oath there is no mention to be made of <hi>Saints.</hi> The reaſon is gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:18971:22"/>
by <hi>Melancthou, Becauſe they</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ne facienda mentio ſancto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum in iuramen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, quia nec ſunt omnipotentes, nec inſpectores cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dium, nec execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tores poenae.</hi> Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancth. in Mat. 5.</note> 
               <hi>are neither emnipotent, nor ſeers of the heart, nor executioners of puniſhment.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note n="*" place="margin">4 All <hi>impious</hi> and <hi>fearefull</hi> Oathes by the parts or ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuncts of Chriſt.</note> The fourth kind here reproued, are <hi>impious and fearefull Oaths,</hi> which (me thinketh) I am afraid to menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>blaſphemous, horrible, terrible,</hi> by the parts or adiuncts of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> as by his <hi>life, death, paſſion, fleſh, heart, wounds, blood, bones, armes, ſides, guts, nailes, foote,</hi> with many hundred more, vvhich a gracious heart can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but melt to heare, tremble to ſpeake, quake to thinke, and yet (good Lord) how common are they in the mouthes of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane <note place="margin">Common in the mouthes of the ſonnes of <hi>Belial.</hi> Whereby they deale vvith Chriſt, 1 Worſe then <hi>Iudas,</hi> Matth. 26. 15.</note> ſonnes of <hi>Beliall,</hi> whereby they peirce the ſides, wound the heart, teare the ſoule, and rend in pieces the body of our bleſſed <hi>Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our;</hi> worſe then <hi>Iudas,</hi> who betraied him to be crucified for mony: theſe crucifie him themſelues meerely vpon vanitie: worſe then the <hi>Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 Worſe then the <hi>Souldiers,</hi> Matth. 27. 35.</note> that diuided his garments; theſe diuide his perſon, his natures, his
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:18971:22"/>
members: worſe then the <hi>Iewes,</hi> who cryed to <hi>Pilate, Crucifie him:</hi> theſe in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtead <note place="margin">3 Worſe then the <hi>Iewes,</hi> Mat. 27. 23.</note> of Croſſe &amp; Nailes, do between their owne teeth grinde him, and <note place="margin">1</note> teare him. They did it <hi>ignorantly,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2</note> theſe <hi>wilfully:</hi> they but once; theſe <note place="margin">Acts 3. 17.</note> often: they in his humiliation; theſe <note place="margin">3</note> after his exaltation. Wherefore as <note place="margin">4</note> theſe commit the greater ſinne, ſo they muſt expect the greater con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation. Thinke vpon this, oh impious blaſphemer, and be <hi>pricked</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Let ſvvearers ruminate vpon this.</note> vvith remorſe for this crying ſinne, as at <hi>Peters</hi> Sermon many <hi>Iewes</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Acts 3. 37.</note> were for their ſinne: otherwiſe know and be aſſured, that it ſhall be eaſier for thoſe that crucified <hi>Chriſt</hi> at the day of iudgement, then for thee.</p>
            <p>The fift and laſt kinde heere re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proued, <note place="margin">5 All ridicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous and nevv fangled Oaths.</note> are <hi>ridiculous Oaths:</hi> too fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent in the mouthes of ſimple Ide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ots in the Country; as, <hi>by my fey, lakin, bodikin, by Cock and Pie,</hi> and diuers ſuch like Oathes (which I am not much acquainted with) foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh, trifling, toyiſh, childiſh. Many
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:18971:23"/>
there are, that inuent ſuch as theſe, and thinke they may haue a Licenſe and Paſport for them, when the Name of God is not expreſſed: but, ſaith <hi>Caluin, While men will bee ſo</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Atqui dum in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genioſi eſſe ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mines volunt, vt fucum faciant Deo, nihil quam friuolis cauilla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionibus ſe ipſos deludunt,</hi> Calu. in Iacob. 5. 12.</note> 
               <hi>witty as to deceiue God, by their vaine cauils they deceiue themſelues.</hi> They muſt not looke for this ere the more to be excuſed, ſince it is no other thing but a <hi>mocking</hi> of God, and <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaning</hi> of his name in theſe ridicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous toyes ſecretly inſinuated. Know therefore, that in a trifle, thou muſt not ſweare at all. In a matter of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance that requireth an Oath, thou mayſt, and muſt vſe the name of GOD reuerently and religiouſly. So we ſee in the ſecond place Oathes are <hi>vnlawfull,</hi> when by any other thing then God.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, <hi>vnlawfull,</hi> when not in <note place="margin">3 Vnlavvfull vvhen not in truth.</note> 
               <hi>Truth:</hi> and in this kinde we may of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend two wayes. Firſt, when our <hi>tongue</hi> diſagreeth with the <hi>thing.</hi> Secondly, when our <hi>mind</hi> diſagreeth with our <hi>tongue.</hi> Firſt, vvhen
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:18971:23"/>
               <hi>our tongue</hi> diſagreeth with the <hi>thing,</hi> not ſpeaking as it is, or as it is vpon <note place="margin">And that, 1 When our tongue diſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeth vvith the thing.</note> certainety, but too ſodainely and raſhly, as we imagine &amp; coniecture.</p>
            <p>And herein a number are very faultie, who being carryed away <note place="margin">A common fault.</note> with their owne imagination, when they haue no ſure ground for what they ſpeake, yet aduenture to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme it with an Oath.</p>
            <p>Secondly (which is vvorſe) when <note place="margin">2 When our minde diſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeth vvith our tongue.</note> our <hi>Minde</hi> diſagreeth with our <hi>Tongue,</hi> not thinking as we ſpeake, but entending to deceiue thoſe to vvhom vvee ſweare. The former of it ſelfe may be <hi>frailtie</hi> and <hi>infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie:</hi> but being ioyned with this <note place="margin">This is flat per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iurie, vvhich God abhorreth, forbiddeth, reproueth.</note> latter it becommeth flat <hi>Periurie.</hi> And this is an horrible and grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous ſinne, which the Lord <hi>abhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth, Zach.</hi> 8. 17. and ſtraitly <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biddeth, Leuit.</hi> 19. 12. and ſharply <note place="margin">Zach. 8. 17.</note> 
               <hi>reproueth, Iere.</hi> 7. 9. <note place="margin">Leuit. 19. 12.</note>
            </p>
            <p>And this is the cauſe (ſaith Saint <note place="margin">Ier. 7. 9.</note> 
               <hi>Auguſtine)</hi> wee are forbidden to ſweare <hi>at all,</hi> not <hi>becauſe all Swea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring</hi>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:18971:24"/>
               <hi>is a ſinne, but becauſe forſwea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Non quia iurare peccatum eſt ſed quia peierare im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane peccatum eſt, à quo longe nos eſſe voluit, qui omnino ne iu. remus admonuit.</note> 
               <hi>is an horrible ſinne, from which hee would haue vs to be very farre, who hath warned vs not to ſweare at all.</hi> And that not vvithout ſpeciall cauſe and reaſon. For it is a ſinne in the higheſt degree, and containeth in it many capitall ſinnes. If there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <note place="margin">Aug. in Mat. 5.</note> as <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſaith, <hi>Mat.</hi> 12. wee <note place="margin">Mat. 12. 36.</note> ſhall <hi>giue an account of euery idle word,</hi> much more of euery falſe word: and if of euery falſe word, much more of euery falſe Oath. <hi>To lye, of it ſelfe, is a ſinne,</hi> ſaith <hi>Muſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culus.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Mentiri per ſe malum eſt. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum hoc acceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>one iuramenti duplicatur.</note> 
               <hi>To adde an Oath to it is a double ſinne.</hi> The Prophet complai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth of thoſe that <hi>ſpeake deceit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully. Pſal.</hi> 12. 2. how much worſe <note place="margin">Wolf. Muſcul. append. ad Pſal. 15. de Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram.</note> are they that ſweare <hi>deceitfully?</hi> their ſinne muſt needes be very dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous. <note place="margin">Pſal. 12. 2.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Now, of this <hi>falſe Swearing</hi> there <note place="margin">Of Periurie there are diuers kindes.</note> are diuers kindes, all which are very haynous: for an Oath being two<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold (as I ſhewed before) <hi>promiſſorie</hi> and <hi>aſſertorie,</hi> vvee are to know,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:18971:24"/>
that this ſinne may be in eyther of <note place="margin">1 In an Oath promiſſorie tvvo vvayes.</note> them. Firſt, in a <hi>promiſſorie Oath,</hi> and that two wayes: firſt, when by Oath wee <hi>promiſe</hi> that vve neuer <note place="margin">1 When vvee promiſe by Oath that vvee intend not.</note> meane to <hi>performe.</hi> Secondly, when hauing meant it ſimply at the Oath taking, wee afterward vnconſtantly <note place="margin">2 When vvee intend at the Oath taking, but after change.</note> change our purpoſe, the thing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing neyther vnlawfull nor impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, but onely inconuenient: both theſe are no ſmall ſinnes, whether done in plaine or cunning manner.</p>
            <p>What ſhall vvee ſay then to that <hi>impious doctrine</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> of <note place="margin">Hence is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proued,</note> 
               <hi>Rome,</hi> which teacheth that <hi>a man ought not to hold faith with Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tikes,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 The impious doctrine of the Church of Rome.</note> whom they ſtile ſuch as pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe the <hi>Apoſtolike</hi> faith, reiect their idle inuentions, and renounce that <hi>Antichriſtian Synagogue?</hi> by the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertaining of which doctrine, Gods Name and Maieſtie is abuſed, fraud and treacherie maintained, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracts betweene Nation and Nation ouer-turned.</p>
            <p>And vvhat ſhall wee ſay to that
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:18971:25"/>
               <hi>impious practiſe</hi> of the <hi>Pope</hi> of <note place="margin">2 The impious practiſe of the Pope of <hi>Rome.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Rome,</hi> who making himſelfe equall vvith God, challengeth to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe power to diſpenſe vvith a law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Oath, and to diſcharge Subiects from their ſworne Allegiance to <hi>Chriſtian Princes?</hi> What is it elſe, but a direct croſſing of Gods ſacred <hi>Maieſtie,</hi> vvho hath giuen expreſſe charge to <hi>performe our Oathes,</hi> as <note place="margin">Mat. 5. 33.</note> being made not onely to man but <note place="margin">Exod. 22. 11.</note> to God: and therefore called, <hi>An</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 Sam. 20. 8.</note> 
               <hi>Oath of the Lord, Exod.</hi> 22. 11. So <note place="margin">2 Sam. 21. 7.</note> that our Oath muſt be performed <note place="margin">Ezek. 17. 19. <hi>Iuramentum eti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am hoſti ſeruan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum: non enim conſiderandum eſt cui, ſed per quem iuras.</hi> Hierom.</note> to our very enemie. And <hi>Ierome</hi> giueth the reaſon, <hi>for you muſt not conſider to whom, but by whom you ſweare.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whence vvee may boldly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, that notwithſtanding the <hi>Popes</hi> relaxation, who hath no li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie to <hi>looſe,</hi> when GOD hath <hi>bound;</hi> no power to <hi>ſeperate,</hi> when <note place="margin">Mat. 19. 6.</note> God hath <hi>coupled;</hi> no authoritie to <hi>releaſe</hi> any lawfull Oath, vvherein is not onely a bond of man to man,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:18971:25"/>
but of man to God: notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding (I ſay) this, our <hi>Ieſuites, Prieſts</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ieſuites, Prieſts and other Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts, vvho breake their Oath of Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giance (not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvithſtanding the Popes Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpenſation) are guiltie of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iurie.</note> &amp; other <hi>Papiſts,</hi> who hauing ſworne Allegiance to the <hi>Kings Maieſtie,</hi> (as next vnder God) <hi>in theſe Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions Supreame Gouernour)</hi> doe af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward violate this lawfull Oath, denying his Supremacie, and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining the <hi>Popes,</hi> are guiltie of this horrible ſinne of periurie. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it vvere to be vviſhed, they vvould herein follow the patterne of the auncient <hi>Romanes,</hi> though <hi>Heathens,</hi> vvhoſe integritie was <note place="margin">The fidelitie of auncient Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manes.</note> ſuch, that they would not breake Oath vvith their deadlieſt Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies.</p>
            <p>Amongſt the reſt, memorable is the Example of <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tilius Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulus,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Tit. Liu. Aul. Gel. Valer. Max.</note> vvho to keepe his Oath made to the <hi>Carthaginians,</hi> his <note place="margin">A rare Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</note> mortall enemies, returned Priſoner to <hi>Carthage.</hi> And though not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled for any other cauſe but his Oath: yet (as <hi>Tully</hi> ſaith of him) <hi>the loue neyther of his Country, nor of</hi>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:18971:26"/>
               <hi>his owne, with-held him, when withall</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ne<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> eum cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritas Patriae reti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuit, nec ſuorum: neqùe vero tum ignorabat, ſe ad crudeliſſimum hoſtem, &amp; ad exquiſita ſuppli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cia proficiſci.</note> 
               <hi>hee knew hee ſhould goe to a most cruell enemie, and to exquiſite Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments;</hi> which afterward hee ſuſtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned till hee dyed, in the cruelleſt and bloudieſt manner that could be inuented. A ſhame then is it for <note place="margin">Cic. de Offic. Lib. 3.</note> 
               <hi>Chriſtians</hi> to come ſhort of <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens,</hi> whoſe onely guide vvas the light of Nature. And ſo much for <hi>Periurie</hi> in the firſt kinde.</p>
            <p>The ſecond kinde of <hi>Periurie</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 In an Oath aſſertorie, tvvo vvayes.</note> is <hi>in an Oath aſſertorie:</hi> and that when wee ſweare eyther <hi>a knowne vntruth:</hi> or an <hi>vnknowne truth.</hi> The firſt is, when vvee ſweare that to be <note place="margin">1 When vvee ſvveare a knovvne vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truth.</note> truth, which is certainly knowne to be vntruth. The ſecond, when vve ſweare that for truth which for the <note place="margin">2 When vvee ſvveare an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knovvne truth.</note> preſent wee ſurely imagine a falſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, though in time to come it proueth to be truth.</p>
            <p>So then it is plaine and manifeſt that in an <hi>Oath</hi> whether <hi>promiſing</hi> 
               <note place="margin">What Periurie is properly.</note> or <hi>affirming, Periurie</hi> is not ſo much ſwearing a thing <hi>falſe</hi> as ſwearing it
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:18971:26"/>
               <hi>falſely,</hi> when heart and words agree not, and when the end thereof is <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Non enim fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum iurarc, peie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rare eſt: ſed quod ex animi tui ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentia iuraueris.</hi> Cic. de Offic. Lib. 3.</note> deceit.</p>
            <p>Vpon vvhat ground then is that Doctrine founded of <hi>Equiuocation,</hi> and <hi>Mentall reſeruation,</hi> which our double harted Aduerſaries do both <note place="margin">Againſt the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of Equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uocation.</note> teach and practiſe in time of dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger. Whereby they iuſtifie that wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked ſpeech in <hi>Euripides,</hi> deteſted of the very <note n="*" place="margin">Cic. Lib. 3. de Offic.</note> 
               <hi>Heathen</hi> themſelues. <note n="a" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Iuraui lingua, mentem iniura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam gero.</hi> Eurip.</note> 
               <hi>I haue ſworne with my tongue, but not with my minde.</hi> Like the fraudulent Oath of <note n="b" place="margin">Plutar. in La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>con.</note> 
               <hi>Cleomenes,</hi> with his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, who ſware a Truce for three dayes, and when they leaſt thought on him, hee ſet vpon them and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed them in the night. Such are the Oathes of our periured <hi>Prieſts</hi> and <hi>Ieſuites;</hi> (I can tearme them no better) who haue a tongue for the <hi>Prince,</hi> and an heart for the <hi>Pope,</hi> deſiring diuelliſhly to deceiue thoſe to whom they ſweare. Which opinion and practiſe being admitted and receiued, doth not onely ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:18971:27"/>
the end of a lawfull Oath, <note place="margin">Which opinion and practiſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing admitted, takes avvay the end of a lavvfull Oath.</note> (which is the deciding of ſtrife, and confirming of truth) but excludeth the Authors of it from <hi>Gods holy Mountaine:</hi> For, hee onely ſhall reſt there, ſaith the <hi>Prophet Dauid,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">And excludeth the Authors of it out of Gods Kingdome. Pſal. 24. 4. Exhortation.</note> 
               <hi>who hath not ſworne deceitfully, Pſal.</hi> 24. 4. <hi>But ſpeaketh the truth in his heart.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For our ſelues therefore that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to pertake of the ioyes of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, let vs be exhorted in the feare of God, <hi>to follow the truth in loue,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Epheſ. 4. 15.</note> and to beware of this ſinne of Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iurie, in what kinde ſoeuer. And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is a ſinne:
<list>
                  <item>1 <hi>Iniurious to God.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2 <hi>Pernicious to our Neighbour.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3 <hi>Dangerous to our ſelues.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>iniurious to God,</hi> and that in diuers <note place="margin">Reaſon 1. Iniurious to God.</note> reſpects:</p>
            <p>Firſt, in <hi>Lying,</hi> vvhich God <hi>ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth, Pro.</hi> 6. 17. And in <hi>defrauding</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1</note> vvhich God <hi>reuengeth.</hi> 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4. 6. <note place="margin">In Lying and defrauding. Prou 6. 17. 1 Theſ. 4. 6.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>in defiling his bleſſed</hi>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:18971:27"/>
               <hi>Name,</hi> by making that a ſhelter for <note place="margin">2 In deſiling his bleſſed Name.</note> lyes: vvhich is as much as if the <hi>Keeper of the Kings Seale,</hi> ſhould ſeale therewith Letters of Treaſon: ſo is it no leſſe treaſon to the <hi>King of</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Which is trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to the King of Kings.</note> 
               <hi>Kings,</hi> to ſeale and confirme a lye vvith his name, vvhich of it ſelfe is <hi>a Tower, and Sunctuary</hi> of veritie, <hi>Prou.</hi> 18. 10. <note place="margin">Prou. 18. 10.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, <hi>in abuſing his glorious</hi> 
               <note place="margin">3 In abuſing his glorious Maieſtie.</note> 
               <hi>Maieſtie,</hi> by making him a partie in the ſinne, and ſo contrarie to himſelfe, as though hee were like the <hi>Diuell, the father of lyes, Iohn</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Iohn 8. 44: <hi>Quid enim re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtat Domino, vbi ſua veritate fue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit ſpoliatus? Iam Deus eſſe deſinet.</hi> Cal. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtit. lib 2. Cap. 8. Sect. 24.</note> 8. 44. And vvhat doe they herein, but ouerthrow his very eſſence? for, <hi>take away his truth, hee ecaſeth to be God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, <hi>in contemning his feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full threatnings,</hi> denounced againſt all that offend in this ſinne: for what doth the periured perſon, but deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rately <note place="margin">4 In contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning his feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings.</note> tempt God, and (as it were) out-face him, prouoke, and dare him, according to his Word to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flict <note place="margin">The periured perſon dareth God.</note> vpon him the deſerued venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:18971:28"/>
which in his Oath hee calleth for, if he ſweare falſely.</p>
            <p>So we ſee in how many reſpects this ſinne is a diſhonour to GOD. Whence <hi>Ioſhua</hi> to bring <hi>Achan</hi> to confeſſion of the truth, ſaith, <hi>My ſonne, giue glory to the Lord God of</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ioſh. 7. 19.</note> 
               <hi>Iſrael, Ioſh.</hi> 7. 19. Intimating, that by periurie God is greatly diſhono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red.</p>
            <p>Secondly, as it is <hi>iniurious to</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Reaſon 2 Pernicious to our neighbour.</note> 
               <hi>God,</hi> ſo <hi>pernicious to our neighbour.</hi> For hereby is the end of an Oath fruſtrated; diſcord preſerued, falſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood erected, iniuſtice maintained. And it is yet more pernicious, if in <note place="margin">And moſt of all, vvhen in publike place of Iudgement, for there is vvrong done 1 To the Iury.</note> publike place of iudgement: for there the periured perſon doth wrong to diuers. Firſt, <hi>to the Iurie,</hi> in drawing them to giue wrong ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict. Secondly, <hi>to the Magiſtrate,</hi> in drawing him to giue wrong iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. <note place="margin">2 To the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate.</note> Thirdly, <hi>to his Neighbour,</hi> who is hereby much wronged and <note place="margin">3 To our Neighbour.</note> iniured.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:18971:28"/>
Either:
<list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>In his ſtate, and goods.</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">1</note>
                  </item>
                  <item>Or, <hi>In his name, and credit.</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">2</note>
                  </item>
                  <item>Or, <hi>In his body and life.</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">3</note>
                  </item>
                  <item>Or, <hi>In his ſoule and ſaluation.</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">4</note>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, and laſtly, it is a ſinne, as <note place="margin">Reaſon 3. Dangerous to ourſelues.</note> 
               <hi>iniurious to God,</hi> and <hi>pernicious to our Neighbour,</hi> ſo <hi>dangerous to ourſelues.</hi> For, by periurie men becomming <hi>Diuels incarnate;</hi> nay, in this regard <note place="margin">Periured per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, Diuels incarnate,</note> beyond the diuel himſelfe (of whom vve haue not heard that euer he abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the name of God to confirme his lyes, but <hi>fathers</hi> them himſelfe) they <note place="margin">Iohn 8. 44.</note> muſt needs draw downe the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of God vpon them. In the midſt whereof (as one ſaith) they finde and feele that that God whom <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Experiuntur enim periuri in medijs poenis, Deum quem in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uocarunt, vere eſſe iratum te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtem, ac vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cem ipſorum per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidiae.</hi> Theſaur. Theol. Matth. Vogel.</note> they haue inuocated is a ſore angry witneſſe, &amp; reuenger of their falſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood: for ſo hee threatneth to be a <hi>ſwift witneſſe againſt falſe ſwearers, Mala.</hi> 3. 5. and that very iuſtly: for an Oath conſiſting not onely of <hi>inuocation,</hi> whereby they call God to witneſſe, but alſo of <hi>imprecation,</hi>
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:18971:29"/>
whereby they call him to reuenge, and binde themſelues to puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment if they ſweare falſely; iuſtly <note place="margin">Iuſtly doth God puniſh periured per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons,</note> may God take them at their word, and execute vpon them the deſired and deſerued vengeance. Whence it <note place="margin">1 Here, and that.</note> is, that he puniſheth them both <hi>here</hi> and <hi>hereafter.</hi> Firſt, <hi>here,</hi> and that <note place="margin">1 Invvardly. <hi>Introſpice in mentem illius, qui ſit ſatſo iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raturus: vide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis enim illam non poſſe acquieſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere, ſed tumul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuari, pertur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bari, ſeipſam in crimen vocare, omni contumeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arum &amp; co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>iti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> genere vex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ari.</hi> Phil. Iu. de dec praec.</note> both <hi>inwardly,</hi> and <hi>outwardly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>inwardly,</hi> with a wounded conſcience (and that at the very act) which whoſoeuer feeleth, nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth no other <hi>Iailor or Hang-man. Doe but looke</hi> (ſaith <hi>Philo) into the minde of him, who is about to ſweare falſely, you ſhall ſee that it cannot be at quiet, but vexed, troubled, of it ſelfe accuſed, and tormented with all kinde of checkes and rebukes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>outwardly;</hi> and that diuers wayes: as <note place="margin">2 Outvvardly.</note> with loſſe<list>
                  <item>1 <hi>Of eſtate.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2 <hi>Of good name.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3 <hi>Of libertie.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>4 <hi>Of life.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:18971:29"/>
Firſt, ſometime with <hi>loſſe of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 Sometime vvith loſſe of Eſtate. Zach. 5. 4.</note> And ſo much the Lord threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, <hi>Zach.</hi> 5. 4. where hee ſaith that <hi>the curſe ſhall enter into the houſe of him that falſely ſweareth by his Name; and it ſhall remaine in the midst of his houſe, and ſhall conſume it with the Timber the cof, and ſtones thereof.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, ſometime with <hi>loſſe of good Name;</hi> which the <hi>Wiſe man</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 Sometime vvith loſſe of good Name.</note> telleth vs, is <hi>to be choſen aboue riches, Prou.</hi> 22. 1. Yet this hath beene ſo <note place="margin">Prou. 22. 1.</note> ſtained by Periurie, with ſuch a blot and blemiſh of infamie, as could ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer be wiped out vntill death; nay, hath often remained long after death. And ſurely it ſtands with <note place="margin">And it ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth vvith great equitie.</note> 
               <hi>great equitie,</hi> that thoſe who get cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit to their falſhood by diſhonou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring God, ſhould haue the diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour turned vpon their owne heads.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, ſometime with <hi>loſſe of Libertie.</hi> And thus was King <note place="margin">3 Sometime vvith loſſe of Libertie.</note> 
               <hi>Zedechiah</hi> puniſhed for the Oath broken with <hi>Nebuchadnezar:</hi> in
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:18971:30"/>
regard whereof, ſaith the Lord, <hi>Ezech.</hi> 17. 19. <hi>As I liue, I will ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly bring mine Oath that hee bath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſed,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ezek. 17. 19.</note> 
               <hi>and my Couenant that he hath broken, vpon his owne head.</hi> And ſo it came to paſſe, for <hi>Nebuchad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nezar</hi> by an Armie <hi>ouer-tooke him,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 Kin. 25. 5. 6. 7</note> 
               <hi>ſlew his Sonnes</hi> before him, <hi>put out both his eyes, and carryed him to Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bell,</hi> as it is in 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 25.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, ſometime with <hi>loſſe of</hi> 
               <note place="margin">4 Sometime vvith loſſe of Life.</note> 
               <hi>Life.</hi> Thus did God puniſh the Oath broken with the <hi>Gibeonites,</hi> not onely with famine three yeeres together, but with the death of <hi>Sauls ſeauen ſonnes, who were hanged vp</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 Sam. 21. 1. 9.</note> 
               <hi>openly in the Mountaine,</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 21.</p>
            <p>And to this purpoſe vvee may reade of, and it vvere not amiſſe <note place="margin">Examples here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of haue beene in this our Land.</note> to mention ſome examples of latter times in this our Land. As of <hi>Earle Godwine,</hi> who vviſhing at the Kings Table, that the Bread might choake <note place="margin">Earle <hi>Godwine.</hi>
               </note> him, if hee were guiltie of <hi>Alphreds</hi> death, vvhom he had before ſlaine, was preſently choaked, and fell<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>downe
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:18971:30"/>
dead. So of a Widdow in <hi>Cornehill,</hi> who hauing ſworne to <note place="margin">Wid. <hi>Barnes, Corn.</hi> in <hi>Lond.</hi> 1574.</note> deceiue a poore <hi>Orphane</hi> of her right, within foure dayes after, caſt herſelfe out at a window; and brake her necke. So of the Woman with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <hi>Alderſgate,</hi> who hauing for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſworne her ſelfe for Flaxe bought <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Anne Aueris,</hi> Wid. <hi>Feb.</hi> 11. 1575.</note> in <hi>Wood-ſtreete,</hi> had (as ſhee deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red) Gods iudgement ſhewed vpon <note place="margin">A pittifull ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample.</note> her, vvas ſodainely ſtricken, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued ſome few dayes in grieuous torments, and ſo wretchedly dyed. Many ſuch examples might be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged; but to theſe giue me leaue onely to adde one more, of which wee reade in <hi>Eccleſiaſticall Hiſtorie,</hi> and it is worthy here to be recorded.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Euſebius</hi> reporteth of three lewd <note place="margin">Three levvd varlets that falſely accuſed <hi>Narciſſus, Euſ. Eccleſ. Hiſt. lib.</hi> 6. <hi>cap.</hi> 8.</note> varlers, that charged <hi>Narciſſus, Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of Ieruſalem,</hi> with a grieuous accuſation, and the better to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade it, confirmed it with Oaths. The firſt, (if it wore not true) wiſhed to be <hi>burnt to aſhes:</hi> the ſecond, to be <hi>tarmented with ſome cruell diſeaſe:</hi>
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:18971:31"/>
the third, to be <hi>ſmitten with blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</hi> Innocent <hi>Narciſſus,</hi> being too weake to reſiſt them, remoued, and hid himſelfe in deſart places for ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny <note place="margin">The iuſtice of God againſt periured per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons.</note> yeres. In the meane time, this hapned to thoſe periured perſons. The firſt by the fall of one ſpark <note place="margin">1</note> of fire in the night, had himſelfe, houſe, and familie <hi>conſumed to aſhes:</hi> The ſecond was <hi>tormented</hi> in his <note place="margin">2</note> whole body, <hi>with the ſame diſeaſe hee wiſhed.</hi> The third, ſeeing their <note place="margin">3</note> ends, and fearing vengeance, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed the miſchiefe, and for it mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and wept, till hee <hi>loſt both his eyes.</hi> A lamentable <hi>ſpectacle</hi> for falſe Witneſſes, and periured per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons. So we ſee how God puniſheth them here.</p>
            <p>Secondly, much more ſeuerely <note place="margin">2 Hereafter.</note> 
               <hi>hereafter:</hi> if he doe not puniſh them <hi>temporally,</hi> then (which is worſe) <hi>eternally.</hi> Vnleſſe here they appeaſe his anger (as <hi>Peter</hi> did) with Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance <note place="margin">Mat. 26. 75.</note> and Teares, they may aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure themſelues of it, they cannot
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:18971:31"/>
auoide it. Let them in this life e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcape the <hi>Wound of Conſcience</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in; and without, loſſe of <hi>Eſtate,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Vnleſſe they repent, they incurre loſſe of Heauen.</note> 
               <hi>Name, Libertie</hi> or <hi>Life:</hi> they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not eſcape the loſſe of <hi>Heauen.</hi> But as they by this ſinne haue renounced God, and giuen vp <note place="margin">They ſhall be giuen vp into the hands of Sathan:</note> themſelues vnto Sathan: ſo for this ſinne God ſhall renounce them, and giue them vp into the hands of Sathan, the Prince of darkeneſſe. And no maruell: for they farre ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe Lyers in iniquitie, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <note place="margin">And haue their portion vvith lyers in the Lake, &amp;c.</note> may well looke for the ſame portion and that I, <hi>in the Lake that burneth with fire and Brimſtone. Reuel.</hi> 21. 8.</p>
            <p>And yet notwithſtanding, how <note place="margin">Application. A ſinne com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon.</note> common a ſinne? and how largely ſpread, ouer euery part of this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and euery corner of this Citie, the <hi>eye</hi> of the Land, and <hi>beautie</hi> of the Kingdome? In publike <hi>Courts of Iudgement,</hi> may not mony hyre <note place="margin">In Courts of Iudg ment. In ſhops and houſes.</note> it<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> in priuate <hi>Shops,</hi> and <hi>Houſes</hi> doth not the droſſe of the vvorld
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:18971:32"/>
cauſe it? In open <hi>Faires</hi> and <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kets,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">In Faires and Markets.</note> doe not our couetous Caitifes vſe it? In <hi>euery trifling Bargaina,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">In euery tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fling bargaine.</note> will not many a wicked wretch (to make good ſale of wares) by Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iurie ſell his ſoule to Hell? In a word, may wee not finde in <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens</hi> more certaintie, leſſe periu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, <note place="margin">More certainty in Heathens, ſvvearing by falſe Gods: then in Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, ſvvea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring by the true God. Whence iuſtly may God be at controuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie vvith
this <list>
                     <item>Land,</item>
                     <item>Citie.</item>
                  </list>
               </note> ſwearing by <hi>Iupiter, Apollo,</hi> and other falſe Gods, then in <hi>Chriſtians</hi> ſwearing by the true God? How iuſtly then may God proclaime a Controuerſie with <hi>this Land</hi> in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall, with <hi>this Citie</hi> in ſpeciall, which is become a <hi>Denne</hi> for theſe <hi>Wolues</hi> to lurke in, a <hi>Cage</hi> for theſe vncleane <hi>Birds</hi> to keepe in, (giue mee leaue to ſay) a <hi>Stie</hi> for theſe filthy <hi>Swine</hi> to lye in, which vval<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low in this ſinne, and will not part with it; eyther for <hi>God,</hi> to whom it is ſo <hi>iniurious:</hi> or for their <hi>Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour,</hi> to whom ſo <hi>pernicious:</hi> or for <hi>Themſelues,</hi> to whom ſo <hi>dangerous.</hi> So wee ſee in the third place, Oaths are <hi>vnlawfull,</hi> when not <hi>in truth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:18971:32"/>
Fourthly, <hi>vnlawfull</hi> when not <hi>in righteouſneſſe;</hi> and that is, when we <note place="margin">4 Vnlavvfull, vvhen not in righteouſneſſe.</note> ſweare eyther without <hi>iuſt occaſion,</hi> or when the <hi>Matter</hi> it ſelfe is not <note place="margin">1</note> 
               <hi>iuſt</hi> and lawfull: but forbidden by <note place="margin">2</note> God, or elſe not in our power. And <note place="margin">1</note> this is a great and grieuous ſinne, <note place="margin">2</note> for a man to ſweare not in a religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous <note place="margin">He that ſvvea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth muſt take heede of tvvo things, ſaid <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phocles, ne laedat amicos, ne peccet in De<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi>
               </note> minde, <hi>to the glory of God,</hi> and <hi>good of Man,</hi> but that which is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to <hi>Pietie</hi> and <hi>Charitie.</hi> So did <hi>Iezabel:</hi> ſhee ſwore the death of <hi>Elias,</hi> 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 19. 2. So did <hi>Ahab:</hi> hee ſwore the death of <hi>Eliſha,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 Kings 19. 2.</note> 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 6. 31. So did the <hi>Iewes:</hi> they <note place="margin">1 Kings 6. 31. Acts 23. 12. Thus do thoſe that ſvveare re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenge.</note> ſwore the death of <hi>Paul, Act.</hi> 23. 12. Thus alſo doe many in theſe dayes, who vpon euery little wrong, ſweare to be reuenged of their neighbour, and to recompenſe <hi>euill for euill,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Rom. 12. 17. 21</note> which they ſhould <hi>ouercome with goodneſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And in this kinde alſo doe offend <note place="margin">The Monkiſh ſort alſo offend in this kinde.</note> thoſe of the <hi>Monkiſh</hi> profeſſion, who ſweare:
<list>
                  <item>
                     <pb n="56" facs="tcp:18971:33"/>
1 <hi>Perpetuall Chaſtitie.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2 <hi>Voluntary Pouerty.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3 <hi>Regular Obedience.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>All vvhich offend againſt the rule of <hi>righteouſneſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The firſt, <hi>Perpetuall Chaſtitie,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is not in their power, nor <note place="margin">Who ſvveare, 1 Perpetuall Chaſtitie, vvhich depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth vpon the gift of God.</note> dependeth vpon their vvill, but vpon the gift of God. And in this regard, ſaith <hi>Paul, If they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not abſtaine, let them marry.</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7. 9. <note place="margin">1 Cor. 7. 9.</note>
            </p>
            <p>The ſecond, <hi>voluntary Pouertie,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 Voluntary pouertie, vvhich is a breach of Gods ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance.</note> and wilfull beggerie, becauſe it is a breach of Gods ordinance, which is, <hi>that there ſhould be no beggar in Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael, Deut.</hi> 15. 4. <note place="margin">Deut. 15. 4.</note>
            </p>
            <p>The third, <hi>Regular Obedience</hi> to <note place="margin">3 Regular O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience, vvhich is a thraldome of the conſcience. Marke 7. 7.</note> the will of Superiours, becauſe it is a thraldome of the Conſcience to the <hi>ordinances of men,</hi> when in regard thereof vvee are onely bound vnto GOD: in vvhich ſence, ſaith the <hi>Apoſtle, Bee not</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 7. 23.</note> 
               <hi>the Seruants of Men,</hi> 1 <hi>Corinth.</hi> 7. 23.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:18971:33"/>
All theſe kindes of Oathes are againſt <hi>Righteouſneſſe:</hi> and as in <note place="margin">As the making ſo the keeping of theſe Oaths are againſt righteouſneſſe. <hi>Quod male iura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, peius ſerua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur.</hi>
               </note> the making, ſo in the keeping: Nay, <hi>that which is ill ſworne, is worſe obſerued.</hi> If the thing ſworne bee eyther vnlawfull, or impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, (vvhether it appeare ſo at the firſt, or be diſcerned after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward) <note place="margin">Vnlavvfull Oathes binde not.</note> it is of no effect, and can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not binde vs.</p>
            <p>And here that rule of <hi>Iſidore</hi> is to be remembred: <hi>In euill promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>In malis promiſſis reſcinde fidem: in turpi vot<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> decretum: &amp; quod in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aute vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſti, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> impia eſt promiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſio, quae ſcelere impletur.</hi> Iſid Well did <hi>Dauid</hi> in breaking his Oath.</note> 
               <hi>breake thy faith: in a diſhonest vow change thy decree: and doe not that thou haſt raſhly vowed: wicked is the promiſe, that is performed with weekedneſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Well therefore did <hi>Dauid,</hi> who (in his raſh paſſion) hauing ſworne the death of <hi>Nabal,</hi> did after, by the aduiſe of <hi>Abigail,</hi> breake it: 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 25. And vvic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedly <note place="margin">1 Sam. 25. 32.</note> did <hi>Herod,</hi> (that Murtherer and no Iudge) vvho ſwore not ſo <note place="margin">Wickedly did <hi>Herod</hi> in kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping his Oath. Marke 6. 26.</note> 
               <hi>raſhly,</hi> but performed it as <hi>wickedly, Marke</hi> 6. 26.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:18971:34"/>
It ſtandeth vs then in hand to <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iuſiurandu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culum iniquita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis eſſe non opor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tet.</hi> Pet. Mart. loc. commun.</note> beware of ſwearing irreligiouſly, or <hi>vnrighteouſly:</hi> (for an Oath muſt not be <hi>the bond of iniquuie)</hi> as alſo hauing ſworne ſo, to craue pardon for it, and not to performe it: for that is, firſt, to make God an ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prouer <note place="margin">To keepe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteous Oathes is:</note> of ſinne: ſecondly, to breake our <hi>Oath of Allagiance,</hi> made to <note place="margin">1 To make God an appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer of ſinne.</note> God in Baptiſme, whereby we haue bound our ſelues to obay his will. So vvee ſee in the fourth place, <note place="margin">2 To breake our bond in Baptiſme.</note> Oathes are <hi>vnlawfull,</hi> when not in <hi>righteouſneſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Laſtly, <hi>vnlawfull,</hi> when not in <note place="margin">5 Vnlavvfull, vvhen not in Iudgement. When neyther called thereto by order of Iudgement: nor able vvith Iudgement to diſcerne the nature of an Oath.</note> 
               <hi>iudgement,</hi> but raſhly and vnadui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedly: when neyther called thereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to by order of <hi>Iudgement,</hi> nor able to diſcerne with <hi>Iudgement,</hi> and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, vvhat wee doe when wee ſweare. Whence it commeth to paſſe wee take it in hand ſo fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently, ſo irreuerently. A thing de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſted of the very Heathen. And therefore it was an auncient Decree <note place="margin">Plut. Quaeſt. Roman.</note> obſerued of the <hi>Romanes,</hi> that
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:18971:34"/>
when young men would ſweare by <hi>Hercules,</hi> they ſhould firſt goe out of the houſe, vvherein they <note place="margin">A commend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able order ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued of the Heathen.</note> vvere. A good meanes to keepe them from ſwearing lightly, when they had ſuch time and leaſure to bethinke themſelues. And ſurely, theſe <hi>Heathen</hi> may riſe vp in Iudgement againſt the men of <note place="margin">They may condemne the men of this generation,</note> this generation, &amp; condemne them, who take no ſpace at all to delibe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, but with leſſe regard and reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to the true God, then they had to their falſe Gods, audaciouſly take his Name in their mouthes, filling <note place="margin">Who haue leſſe regard to the true God then they had to their falſe Gods.</note> vp ouery ſentence in ordinary com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication vvith idle, vaine, and vnneceſſary Oathes. So wee ſee in the laſt place, Oathes are <hi>vnlawfull,</hi> when not in <hi>Iudgement.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſo much ſhall ſerue to haue ſhowed what <hi>Oathes</hi> are <hi>lawfull,</hi> what <hi>vnlawfull.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now come vvee to the vſe of <note place="margin">Novv follovv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the vſe of all the former doctrine.</note> the vvhole former doctrine con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning <hi>Oathes,</hi> both <hi>lawfull</hi> and
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:18971:35"/>
               <hi>vnlawfull.</hi> And it affordeth to vs a two-fold vſe:
<list>
                  <item>1 <hi>For information.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2 <hi>For caution.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>For infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation <note place="margin">Vſe 1. For informa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note>
               <list>
                  <item>1 Of our <hi>knowledge.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2 Of our <hi>practiſe.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>And firſt, it ſerueth to <hi>informe</hi> our <hi>knowledge,</hi> that in ſome caſes <note place="margin">1 Of our knovvledge, that in ſome caſes vve may ſvveare. Againſt the er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour of the <hi>Manichees</hi> and <hi>Anabaptiſts,</hi> vvho altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther take avvay the vſe of an Oath. Their allega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, Iam. 5. 12 Matth. 5. 34. The anſvvere.</note> we may ſweare. Contrary to the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion of the <hi>Manichees,</hi> ſince re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newed, and taken vp by the <hi>Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſts,</hi> who altogether reiect the vſe of an Oath, and refuſe it, euen vvhen authoritie requireth it: for the vpholding of which <hi>hereſie,</hi> they cite for their authorit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e, not onely the precept of Saint <hi>Iames, Before all things, my brethren, ſweare not, Iam.</hi> 5. 12. but of <hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelfe, <hi>Sweare <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> at all, Matth.</hi> 5. 34. Whereas both S. <hi>Iames</hi> in the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer and ſo <hi>Chriſt</hi> in the latter doth nor forbid it, but reſtraine it. So that we may not therein vnderſtand <note place="margin">The true mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of our Sauiour.</note> the prohibition of euery kinde of Oath, but onely of <hi>idle Oathes, and</hi>
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:18971:35"/>
               <hi>colluſion of Oathes</hi> (as <hi>Bucer,) or ſwea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring lightly and looſely</hi> (as <hi>Gualther,)</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Bucer in Mat.</hi> 5. <hi>Gual. in Mat. Zanch. in ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tium praecept. Vrſin. Catechiſ. pars</hi> 3.</note> 
               <hi>or ſwearing in common talke</hi> (as <hi>Zan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chius,) or raſh and vnneceſſary Oathes.</hi> (as <hi>Vrſinus,) or priuate and ordinary ſwearing,</hi> (as <hi>Ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tius,</hi> and <hi>Melan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cthon,) or ſwearing by the creatures</hi> (as <hi>Beza,</hi> and <hi>Pellican.)</hi> In a word, it is plaine that the ſcope of our <hi>Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our</hi> is onely to taxe the corruption of the <hi>Phariſees,</hi> vvho thought in their iudgement, and taught in their doctrine, that in the third Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement vvas onely forbidden Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iurie: and no Periurie but vvhen <note place="margin">1</note> there vvas expreſſed the name of <note place="margin">2</note> God, or ſome other thing, immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atly <note place="margin">Matth. 23. 16. 17. 18.</note> pertaining to his ſeruice. Other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, to <hi>ſweare</hi> and <hi>forſweare</hi> by the creatures, they thought no <hi>defiling</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Leuit. 19. 12.</note> 
               <hi>his Name,</hi> nor <hi>taking of it in vaine.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Exod. 20. 7. Our Sauiour chargeth them of a three-fold crime:</note>
            </p>
            <p>But our <hi>Sauiour</hi> herein layeth to their charge both <hi>Idolatrie, Periurie,</hi> and <hi>impietie.</hi> Firſt, <hi>Idolatrie,</hi> in ſwea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring by them, whereby they much <note place="margin">1 Idolatrie. <hi>Hil.</hi> 4 <hi>Can. on Matth.</hi>
               </note> diſhonoured God, in giuing his wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:18971:36"/>
to the creatures. Secondly, <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iurie,</hi> in confirming a falſehood by <note place="margin">2 Periurie. <hi>Ne<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> enim Deus haret in ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bio, ſed mentem iurantis ſpectat, nec tam in ſylla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis, quam in ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentijs, honor &amp; contumelia no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minis diuini con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtit.</hi> Vrſin. Catechiſ. pars.</note> ſuch an Oath, of it ſelfe no true Oath; yet ſo, in the opinion of him that ſweareth, who in this reſpect is counted guiltie. <note n="*" place="margin">3 Impietie.</note> Thirdly, <hi>impietie,</hi> in <note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Colligimus nul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lam creaturam tam paruo nobis eſtimari debere, vt ipſam vano iuramento pollu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amus.</hi> Pell. in Matth.</note> polluting the creatures, by raſh and falſe ſwearing, and ſo (though not directly, yet indirectly) pollu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the name of God: in aſmuch as <note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>Tantum opifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cem deſignant a ſuis operibus,</hi> Caluin. in Iac. 5. 12.</note> by <hi>theſe workes of his</hi> (ſaith <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uin)</hi> 
               <note place="margin">3. quaeſt. 102.</note> 
               <hi>they point out the workeman,</hi> whoſe glory and Maieſtie ſhineth in them, and thus the diſhonour rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth to God himſelfe.</p>
            <p>Now whereas he ſaith <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Sweare not at all,</hi> the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>(at all)</hi> is to haue reference to the formes rehearſed, as by <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, Earth, Ieruſalem,</hi> and ſuch like, <hi>approued</hi> of the <hi>Phariſes, reproued</hi> of <hi>Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherefore, his meaning is, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Omnino</hi> 1. <hi>per vllam rem crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam,</hi> Beza An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not-Maio. in Matth. 5.</note> 
               <hi>Sweare not at all,</hi> that is, not <hi>at all by any creature,</hi> vpon vvhat pretence ſoeuer: nor <hi>at all by God himſelfe,</hi>
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:18971:36"/>
               <hi>falſely</hi> or <hi>vnaduiſedly;</hi> neither <hi>diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deredly,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Nec affectu, vt perturbati: nec imitatione, vt parvuli: nec conſuetudine, vt ſcelerati: nec fictitie, vt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptores,</hi> Pell. in Matth 5.</note> for <hi>affection:</hi> nor <hi>childiſhly,</hi> for <hi>imitation:</hi> nor <hi>deſperatly,</hi> for <hi>cuſtome:</hi> nor <hi>cunningly,</hi> for <hi>deceit:</hi> other Oathes, which faile not in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions required, Saint <hi>Iames</hi> diſli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth not, our <hi>Sauiour</hi> condemneth not, vvhither they be <hi>publike</hi> Oaths, inioyned by authoritie: or <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Priuata iura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menta, quae ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brie, ſancte, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerenter, neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarijs rebus ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibentur, dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nare nimis peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culoſum fuerit.</hi> Caluin. Inſtit. lib 2. cap. 8. ſect. 27.</note> 
               <hi>priuate</hi> Oathes, vſed <hi>vpon neceſſitie, ſoberly, religiouſly,</hi> and <hi>reuerently,</hi> as is plaine by the examples of <note n="a" place="margin">Gen. 31. 53.</note> 
               <hi>Iacob</hi> to <hi>Laban,</hi> of <note n="b" place="margin">1 Sam. 20. 12.</note> 
               <hi>Ionathan</hi> to <hi>Dauid,</hi> of <note n="c" place="margin">Ruth 3. 13.</note> 
               <hi>Booz</hi> to <hi>Ruth,</hi> and diuers other.</p>
            <p>Wee may ſay then to the <hi>Anabap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts,</hi> as <hi>Chriſt</hi> to the <hi>Sadduces, they are deceiued, not knowing the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.</hi> Were that miſinterpretation of theirs allowed, <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſhould haue <hi>condemned</hi> what his Father had <hi>or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained,</hi> and <hi>deſtroyed</hi> the morral law, which hee came to fulfill, <hi>Matth.</hi> 5. 17.</p>
            <p>In the ſecond place therefore, it ſerueth to <hi>informe</hi> our <hi>practiſe:</hi> and it doth inſtruct and teach vs, <hi>not to</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Matt. 22. 29. <hi>Chriſtus dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nare nec voluit, nec potuit, quod pater inſtituit.</hi> Pel. Mat. 5. 17.</note> 
               <note place="margin">2 For infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of our practiſe: it teacheth vs not to feare to take an Oath vpon iuſt occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion. Reaſon</note>
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:18971:37"/>
               <hi>feare to take an Oath,</hi> (when neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie requireth) both <hi>publike</hi> and <hi>priuate:</hi> but willingly to doe it, when there is ſufficient warrant for it: ſo ſhall
<list>
                  <item>1 <hi>A good cauſe be furthered.</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">1</note>
                  </item>
                  <item>2 <hi>Authoritie obayed.</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">2</note>
                  </item>
                  <item>3 <hi>God himſelfe much honoured.</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">3</note>
                  </item>
               </list>
For it is a part of his ſeruice, and ſuch a part as is <note n="*" place="margin">1 King. 8. 31.</note> ſometime put for his whole ſeruice: and therefore to <note place="margin">Pſal. 63. 11.</note> be refuſed no more then <hi>Prayer,</hi> or <note place="margin">Eſa. 48. 1.</note> any other <hi>worſhip</hi> of God. Rightly to ſweare is to ſanctifie his Name, for which the <hi>religious</hi> ſwearer ſhall <note place="margin">The religious ſvvearer ſhall be revvarded.</note> be <hi>rewarded,</hi> as ſurely as the <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane</hi> ſwearer ſhall be <hi>puniſhed.</hi> And ſo much of the vſe for <hi>information.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now as it ſerueth to <hi>informe</hi> vs, ſo withall to <hi>warne</hi> vs: to <hi>warne</hi> vs <note place="margin">Vſe 2. For caution. To bevvare of vaine Oathes.</note> to beware of <hi>vaine</hi> Oathes, and to take heed of <hi>vnlawfull</hi> ſwearing. And the rather for theſe <hi>conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, becauſe it is <hi>a transgreſſing</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Reaſon 1. It is a tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſing of the Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment:</note> 
               <hi>of Gods Commandement.</hi> it is a <hi>ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute</hi>
               <pb n="65" facs="tcp:18971:37"/>
enacted in the high <hi>Court</hi> of <hi>Parliament</hi> in Heauen, by the <hi>King</hi> of <hi>Kings,</hi> and <hi>Lord</hi> of <hi>Lords: Thou</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 Of God the Father.</note> 
               <hi>ſhalt not take the Name of the Lord</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Exod. 20. 7.</note> 
               <hi>thy God in vaine.</hi> Nay more: there is alſo a <hi>threatning</hi> annexed there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto, <note place="margin">Reaſon. For the Lord vvill not holde him guiltleſſe, that taketh his Name in vain.</note> vvhich there is to no other <hi>law,</hi> ſaue onely to the <hi>ſecond:</hi> to ſhew, that as <hi>Idolatry,</hi> ſo the <hi>abuſe of his name</hi> of all other ſinnes ſhall not eſcape iudgement. And from the <hi>Father</hi> come we to the <hi>Sonne,</hi> who in his <hi>Goſpell</hi> will not haue vs to <note place="margin">2 Of God the Sonne.</note> ſweare at all, but to <hi>let our commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Matt. 5. 34. 35. 36. 37. Reaſon. For vvhatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer is more, commeth of euill.</note> 
               <hi>be yea, yea; nay, nay.</hi> And he is not without his <hi>reaſon:</hi> for <hi>whatſoeuer is more commeth of euill.</hi> And Saint <hi>Iames</hi> the <hi>Penman</hi> of the <hi>holy Ghoſt,</hi> is very earneſt in the ſame precept: <hi>before all things, my bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">3 Of God the holy Ghoſt. Iam. 5. 12. Reaſon. Leaſt you fall into condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation.</note> 
               <hi>ſweare not.</hi> And he alſo giueth a good <hi>reaſon, leaſt yee fall into con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domnatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> It behoueth vs then to ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaine from it, in regard of this <hi>Law,</hi> and <hi>Statute,</hi> confirmed with ſuch ſtrong <hi>reaſon,</hi> both by <hi>God the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi>
               <pb n="66" facs="tcp:18971:38"/>
of whom it was <hi>enacted;</hi> and by <hi>God the Sonne,</hi> of whom <hi>ratified,</hi> and by <hi>God the holy Ghoſt,</hi> of whom <hi>renewed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, it is <hi>a great vilifying of God:</hi> be it either by <hi>other things,</hi> or <note place="margin">Reaſon 2. It is a great vilifying of God.</note> by <hi>his Name:</hi> If by <hi>other things,</hi> wee <hi>debaſe him,</hi> in preferring them be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him, and <hi>making him inferiour</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Be it either by other things, Or by his Name,</note> to them. If by his name, wee doe alſo debaſe him, in <hi>making him</hi> a <hi>common</hi> witneſſe, and ſo prophaning him. The <hi>Name</hi> of God is to be <note place="margin">Which is not to be polluted by common vſe.</note> had in high <hi>account,</hi> and great <hi>reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence;</hi> and therefore not to be <hi>pollu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted</hi> by common vſe. <hi>Mercurius Triſmegiſtus</hi> was in ſuch reſpect a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt <note place="margin">Mercu. Triſme. Nomen eius pro prium ob reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentiam quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam pronunciare vulgo, &amp; temere non licebat.</note> the <hi>Egiptians,</hi> that <hi>in reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of him it was not lawfull to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce his name commonly and raſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">Claud. Min. com. in Alciat.</note> 
               <hi>Haro,</hi> Duke of <hi>Normandy,</hi> would haue his <hi>name</hi> ſo <hi>terrible,</hi> that <note place="margin">Marſil. Ficin.</note> at the very hearing of it men ſhould croutch. If the <hi>names</hi> of ſinfull men haue beene had in ſuch <hi>reſpect,</hi> what <hi>reuerence</hi> may wee thinke due to the <hi>name of God?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:18971:38"/>
The <hi>Name of God</hi> (as one ſaith) is a <hi>name</hi> to be feared, a <hi>name</hi> to be <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Nomen terribile, admirabile. lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dabile, terribile, quantum ad pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentiam: admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rabile, quantum ad ſapientiam: laudabile, quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum ad bonita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem.</hi> Bonauent. expoſ. orat. Domin.</note> 
               <hi>admired,</hi> a <hi>name</hi> to be <hi>praiſed:</hi>
               <list>
                  <item>To be <hi>feared</hi> for <hi>power.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>To be <hi>admired</hi> for <hi>wiſedome.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>To be <hi>praiſed</hi> for <hi>goodneſſe.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
And therefore let this <hi>name</hi> be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually in thy mouth, but <hi>(ad pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>candum, non iurandum)</hi> to pray to it, not to ſweare by it; for that is to <hi>debaſe,</hi> and <hi>vilifie</hi> his <hi>Name,</hi> vvho is <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lyra</hi> in his <hi>Gloſſe,</hi> on Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſ. 23. 13.</note> a <hi>great God,</hi> and therefore <hi>fearefull:</hi> a <hi>wiſe</hi> God, and therefore <hi>wonderfull:</hi> a good <hi>God,</hi> and therefore <hi>praiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Deut. 28. 58.</note> So ſaith that ſweet <hi>Singer,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 8. 1.</note> 
               <hi>His Name is to be praiſed, from the</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 113. 3.</note> 
               <hi>riſing of the Sunne to the going downe of the ſame, Pſal.</hi> 113. 3.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, it <hi>peruerteth the vſe of</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Reaſon 3. It peruerteth the vſe of our ſpeech, Which vvas gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen vs to glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifie God.</note> 
               <hi>our ſpeech:</hi> for that was giuen of God to no other end but to ſpeake the language of <hi>Canaan,</hi> and to glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifie our <hi>Creatour.</hi> Now when it paſſeth theſe bounds, limited there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto by creation, and taketh his Name in vaine: this faculty of ſpeech
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:18971:39"/>
is abuſed to the diſhonour of him <note place="margin">By this, it is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſed to the diſhonour of him that gaue it.</note> that gaue it. For, <hi>a wicked thing is it</hi> (ſaith <hi>Philo) to ſpeake filthily with that mouth, wherein is vttered the moſt ſacred name of God.</hi> It <hi>defileth</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſt namque im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pium eo ore tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pia loqui, quo ſacratiſſimum nomen Dei pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fertur.</hi> Phi. Iud. de dec praecep. Reaſon 4. It is the cog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſance of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than, &amp; badge of prophaneſſe.</note> the <hi>mouth,</hi> it <hi>peruerteth</hi> the <hi>ſpeech;</hi> it <hi>abuſeth</hi> the <hi>tongue,</hi> which by right of <hi>creation</hi> ſhould ſerue as a <hi>Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet</hi> to ſound forth his glory.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, <hi>it is the very cogniſance of Sathan,</hi> and <hi>badge</hi> of <hi>prophane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</hi> And ſuch a one as vſeth it, may well be termed a wretched perſon: for hee will make no conſcience of any ſinne, that maketh no con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience of this ſinne, this <hi>vaine</hi> ſinne, <note place="margin">Svvearing, a more vaine ſinne then any other.</note> for excuſe whereof he hath not any ſhew of <hi>outward good</hi> to pleade: nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>credit,</hi> as the malicious <hi>reuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger:</hi> nor <hi>profit,</hi> as the couetous <hi>Vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer:</hi> nor <hi>preferment,</hi> as the diſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling <hi>flatterer:</hi> nor <hi>pleaſure,</hi> as the vncleane <hi>adulterer.</hi> Wee may well <note place="margin">Hee that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth no con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience of this, vvill make no conſcience of other.</note> thinke then that the common ſwea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer will not ſticke at any of theſe ſinnes, vnleſſe more for diſgrace
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:18971:39"/>
and danger, then for any feare of God. Hee that will ſinne for <hi>nothing,</hi> vvill ſinne for <hi>ſomething:</hi> and what dare not hee doe, that dare pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane Gods holy <hi>Name,</hi> wearing it, and tearing it like his old cloathes? It is therefore a ſure ſigne, ſet<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>downe by <hi>Salomon,</hi> as of a <hi>godly</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Eccleſ. 9. 2.</note> man, <hi>to feare an Oath,</hi> ſo of a <hi>wicked</hi> man not to reſpect it. <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 9. 2.</p>
            <p>I haue read of an <hi>Harlot,</hi> vvho hauing three ſonnes, tolde her huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deſtruct. vitioru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  </hi> pars 4. cap. 17.</note> that one of them onely vvas <note place="margin">A fit example for this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe.</note> his: whereupon at his death he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queathed his eſtate to him, vvho ſhould be found out to be his na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall ſonne. The Sonnes fell at con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention: the matter came to tryall: The <hi>Iudge</hi> to decide it, commanded that their Fathers dead body ſhould be ſet againſt a tree, and hee that could ſhoote neareſt his heart, ſhould be his Heyre. The two <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtards</hi> ſhot, the third refuſed it, and was much offended with the other for doing it. By which <hi>naturall loue</hi>
               <pb n="70" facs="tcp:18971:40"/>
they concluded him the <hi>naturall ſonne,</hi> and gaue him the inheritance, So they that truely loue God, and cannot endure but grieue to heare <note place="margin">Thoſe that grieue at the abuſe of Gods name, ſhevv themſelues the ſonnes of God.</note> his <hi>Name</hi> abuſed, ſhew themſelues to be the true <hi>Sonnes</hi> of God, <hi>Cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen</hi> in Chriſt, <hi>called</hi> to Chriſt, <hi>iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied</hi> by Chriſt, and to be <hi>glorified</hi> with Chriſt: but thoſe wretches that feare not to <hi>wound</hi> Chriſt, and <note place="margin">Thoſe that feare it not, no ſonnes, but ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtards, and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thans ſlaues. 1 Kings 3. 26.</note> to <hi>ſhoote</hi> at his heart with <hi>Oathes,</hi> as with <hi>Arrowes,</hi> crying with the <hi>Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lot, diuide</hi> him, <hi>diuide</hi> him, are no <hi>Sonnes,</hi> but <hi>Baſtards;</hi> no <hi>Sheepe,</hi> but <hi>Goates;</hi> no <hi>Seruants</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> but <hi>Slaues</hi> of <hi>Sathan;</hi> no <hi>heyres</hi> of <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen,</hi> but <hi>fire-brands</hi> of <hi>Hell.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fiftly and laſtly, it is a ſinne, that <hi>maketh vs lyable to the wrath and</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Reaſon. 5. It maketh vs lyable to the vvrath &amp; iudge ment of God.</note> 
               <hi>Iudgement of God.</hi> It is the Word of <hi>Almightie</hi> God himſelfe; <hi>The Lord will not hold him guiltleſſe that taketh his Name in vaine.</hi> And as ſurely as it is <hi>threatned,</hi> ſo it ſhall <note place="margin">Exod. 20. 7.</note> be <hi>executed.</hi> A Sword of vengeance hangeth ouer their heads, and they
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:18971:40"/>
draw downe Iudgements vpon themſelues, both <hi>in this life,</hi> and <hi>in the life to come.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>in this life,</hi> the Lord denoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth <hi>many, great, wonderfull,</hi> and <hi>long</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 In this life.</note> 
               <hi>plagues,</hi> againſt thoſe that <hi>feare not his glorious Name, Deut.</hi> 28. 58. And <note place="margin">Deut. 28. 58. 59. 60. 70. Zach. 5. 1. 2. 3.</note> this the Prophet <hi>Zachariah</hi> in his fift Chapter ſaw in the <hi>viſion</hi> of the <hi>flying Booke,</hi> in <hi>length, twenty cubits,</hi> in <hi>bredth, tenne cubits,</hi> vvherein <note place="margin">A Booke of curſes againſt the Svvearer.</note> were vvritten the <hi>curſes that goe forth againſt the Swearer:</hi> which ſhall <hi>neuer be forgotten,</hi> for they are <note place="margin">They ſhall be remembred:</note> 
               <hi>recorded in a Booke:</hi> they are not <hi>few,</hi> but <hi>many;</hi> for it is a <hi>long</hi> and <hi>broad Booke:</hi> they come <hi>ſwiftly,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">They are many. They come ſvviftly.</note> not <hi>ſlowly:</hi> for, it is a <hi>flying Booke.</hi> And what the <hi>Prophet</hi> ſaith, hath <note place="margin">The flying Booke hath beene ſeene a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt vs, in this Land.</note> not <hi>Experience</hi> found true? hath not this <hi>flying Booke</hi> beene ſeene amongſt vs? <hi>Beloued,</hi> this our <hi>Land</hi> hath not wanted <hi>Examples.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Witneſſe the <hi>Example</hi> of <note n="*" place="margin">Iohn Peter, Fox. Act. &amp; Mon.</note> one <note place="margin">Examples.</note> (of whom vvee may reade in the <hi>Acts</hi> and <hi>Monuments)</hi> that being
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:18971:41"/>
a horrible ſwearer and blaſphemer, it was vſuall with him to ſay, if it be not true, <hi>I pray God I may rot<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ere I dye.</hi> Thus commonly hee tooke Gods Name in vaine, and yet not in vaine: his wiſh was not fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate; for hee <hi>rotted</hi> away indeede and ſo <hi>dyed</hi> in miſerie.</p>
            <p>Witneſſe the Example of the <note n="*" place="margin">A Gentleman of <hi>Cornewall. Ibid.</hi>
               </note> young <hi>Gentleman</hi> of <hi>Cornewall,</hi> who in company with other <hi>Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen,</hi> beganne to ſweare and vſe ribauld ſpeech: being reproued for <note place="margin">In the time of King <hi>Edward.</hi>
               </note> it, hee ſwoore the more, and raged worſe and worſe. At length, paſſing <note place="margin">A vvarning for Gentlemen.</note> ouer a great Bridge, and an arme of the Sea, he ſo ſpurred his horſe, as that hee ſprang cleane ouer vvith the man on his backe, vvho as hee was going, cryed, ſaying, <hi>Horſe, and man, and all to the Diuell.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Witneſſe laſtly, the <hi>Example</hi> (to <note place="margin">A Seruingman in <hi>Lincolneſhire. Perk. Gou. of Tongue.</hi>
               </note> name no more) of a <hi>Seruingman</hi> in <hi>Lincolne-ſhire,</hi> who for euery tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fle had an vſe to ſweare no leſſe Oath, then <hi>Gods precious bloud:</hi>
               <pb n="73" facs="tcp:18971:41"/>
hee would not be warned by his friends to leaue it. At laſt, hee <note place="margin">A vvarning for Seruingmen.</note> was viſited vvith grieuous ſickneſſe; in the time whereof hee could not be perſwaded to repent of it; but hearing the Bell to toll, hee did moſt hardly, in the very anguiſh of death, ſtart vp in his bed, and ſwore by his former Oath, <hi>that Bell tolled for him.</hi> Whereupon immediately, <note place="margin">A lamentable ſpectacle.</note> the bloud abundantly from all the ioynts of his body, as it were in ſtreames, did iſſue out moſt feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, from <hi>mouth, noſe, wreſts, knees, heeles,</hi> and <hi>toes,</hi> with all other ioynts, not one left free, and ſo dyed.</p>
            <p>Mee thinketh, theſe, and ſuch <note place="margin">Fearefull vvar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings.</note> like <hi>fearefull warnings</hi> from heauen ſhould ſinke into the hearts of thoſe, whoſe tongues being ſet on fire of hell, ſpeake nothing without an Oath.</p>
            <p>Oh then <hi>conſider</hi> of theſe, <hi>yee</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 50. 22.</note> 
               <hi>that forget God, leaſt he teare you in pieces, and there be none to deliuer you.</hi> Let theſe be <hi>Examples</hi> to you
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:18971:42"/>
leaſt you be made <hi>Examples</hi> to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</p>
            <p>And yet <hi>alas,</hi> here is not all. Might the Swearer here ſtay, and <note place="margin">2 In the life to come.</note> dye like a bruit beaſt, well were the caſe with him: but here is onely the beginning of his woe. At the houre of death <hi>vengeance waiteth at the doore:</hi> and when his <hi>body</hi> ſhall be <hi>without life,</hi> his <hi>ſoule</hi> ſhall be <hi>with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out God.</hi> In this life God is <hi>patient</hi> toward him, <hi>to lead him to Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 Pet. 3. 9.</note> But if his long ſuffering be abuſed, GOD, ſetteth it vpon the <note place="margin">God ſetteth vpon the ſcore.</note> ſcore, and will one day call him to a fearefull reckoning, the word is paſſed out of his mouth, hee ſhall not be <hi>held guiltleſſe.</hi> He may here happily paſſe without <hi>puniſhment;</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Exod. 20. 7.</note> nay, without <hi>controulement.</hi> But <note place="margin">The Svvearer may paſſe vvith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out puniſhment here:</note> if <hi>Magistrates</hi> (as Gods <hi>Iury</hi> on earth) forgetting the <hi>Iudges</hi> charge, giue vp <hi>falſe verdict,</hi> and cannot finde him guiltie, the chiefe <hi>Iudge</hi> of the world, when at his great ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall <note place="margin">But not here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after.</note> 
               <hi>Aſſiſe</hi> of the whole earth, he
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:18971:42"/>
ſitteth in his <hi>Iudgement Seate</hi> vpon <hi>life</hi> and <hi>death,</hi> will <hi>not hold him guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe,</hi> but <hi>conuict</hi> him, <hi>condemne</hi> him, <note place="margin">The chiefe Iudge ſhall condemne him and commit him to perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in the dungeon of darkneſſe. Marke 9. 44.</note> 
               <hi>pronounce ſentence</hi> againſt him, <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit</hi> him cloſe <hi>Priſoner to Sathan:</hi> Take him <hi>Iaylor, binde</hi> him hand and foot, <hi>caſt</hi> him into the <hi>Dungeon</hi> of <hi>darkneſſe,</hi> there to remaine (with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <hi>baile</hi> or <hi>mainprize)</hi> in perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall <hi>torments, where their worme di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not, and their fire neuer goeth out.</hi> There ſhall be the portion of vngodly Swearers.</p>
            <p>I ſpeake not of thoſe, that may ſeldome <hi>ſlip</hi> therein <hi>by infirmitie,</hi> but of thoſe that <hi>practiſe</hi> it <hi>conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually.</hi> In the one ſort, it is as a rebellious <hi>Seruant:</hi> in the other, as a Lordly <hi>Tyrant.</hi> In ſome it is as a <hi>bad Tenant,</hi> that will not depart <note place="margin">1</note> after many warnings; and as an <hi>vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Svvearing is in ſome as a bad Tenant. Or as an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden Gueſt.</note> 
               <hi>gueſt,</hi> that <hi>intrudeth</hi> himſelfe, and <hi>wanteth</hi> a <hi>roome</hi> to ſit in: theſe though they fall, riſe by repentance, and ſo eſcape Iudgement. In others, it ſitteth as a <hi>King</hi> in his <hi>Throne,</hi>
               <pb n="76" facs="tcp:18971:43"/>
it <hi>raigneth,</hi> it <hi>ruleth,</hi> and <hi>continueth.</hi> Their hardneſſe of heart is ſuch, <note place="margin">2</note> 
               <note place="margin">In others, as a King in his Throne.</note> they make euen a <hi>trade</hi> of <hi>blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming</hi> God, and <hi>grieuing</hi> his <hi>Spirit</hi> by <hi>Helliſh Oaths:</hi> and for theſe <hi>Hell gapeth,</hi> the <hi>Diuell wayteth. Hell ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth</hi> 
               <note place="margin">They make a trade of it.</note> ready to <hi>conſume</hi> them: the <hi>Diuell waiteth</hi> ready to <hi>deuoure</hi> them. If here (while God offereth grace) <note place="margin">And theſe vvithout Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance fall into condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation.</note> they quench not the <hi>flame</hi> of his wrath with the <hi>teares</hi> of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, it ſhall <hi>burne</hi> hotte a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them, and that in hell <hi>Fire:</hi> their <hi>tongues,</hi> and whole <hi>bodies</hi> ſhall for euer be <hi>tormented;</hi> they ſhall continue to <hi>blaſpheme</hi> God among the <hi>damned;</hi> their <hi>portion</hi> is <hi>perdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;</hi> their <hi>end</hi> is <hi>condemnation, Iames</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Iames 5. 12.</note> 5. 12.</p>
            <p>Theſe <hi>Reaſons</hi> then may cauſe vs <hi>to beware of vaine ſwearing;</hi> which <hi>tranſgreſſeth</hi> Gods <hi>Law, vilifieth</hi> his <hi>Name, peruerteth</hi> our <hi>ſpeech,</hi> is the <hi>Cogniſance</hi> of <hi>Sathan,</hi> and <hi>fore-run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner</hi> of <hi>Iudgements</hi> both <hi>temporall</hi> and <hi>eternall.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="77" facs="tcp:18971:43"/>
Now, becauſe notwithſtanding <note place="margin">Novv follovv to be anſvvered the chiefe ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iections al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſvvearing.</note> all this againſt it, <hi>Swearers</hi> thinke they haue ſomething to pleade for it, vvhereby (if not to <hi>defend</hi> it, yet) to <hi>excuſe</hi> it: I ſhall here by your patience, not thinke it amiſſe, to take away the chiefe <hi>obiections</hi> alledged in behalfe of it. To let paſſe their <hi>Scriptures,</hi> vvhich make not for them, but againſt them, allowing onely (as hath beene ſhewed) of a <hi>lawfull,</hi> and <hi>religious Oath:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It will firſt be <hi>obiected,</hi> that it <hi>graceth</hi> their <hi>ſpeech,</hi> and is an <hi>orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Obiect. 1. It is a grace to their ſpeech. Anſvvere. Curſed be ſuch grace, as rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth God of his glory.</note> to their phraſes. But is it a <hi>grace</hi> to thy <hi>ſpeech,</hi> to <hi>diſgrace</hi> him that gaue it? Is it an <hi>ornament</hi> to thy <hi>tongue,</hi> to <hi>diſhonour</hi> him that made it? Curſed bee ſuch <hi>grace, woe</hi> to ſuch <hi>eloquence,</hi> as rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth God of his due <hi>glory.</hi> It is <hi>loathſome</hi> in his <hi>eyes, harſh</hi> in his <hi>eares, ſtinketh</hi> in his <hi>noſthrils.</hi> And ſuch gaine no <hi>credit,</hi> but loſe <hi>reputation: loſe</hi> it with God, <hi>loſe</hi> it <note place="margin">2 Such gaine no credit but loſe it.</note>
               <pb n="78" facs="tcp:18971:44"/>
with thoſe that feare God, and ſhew themſelues to be no <hi>Gallants,</hi> but <hi>ſlaues</hi> and <hi>ſeruants,</hi> euen to <hi>Sathan</hi> himſelfe the <hi>Prince</hi> of <hi>darkeneſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It will ſecondly be <hi>obiected</hi> to be <hi>a generall cuſtome;</hi> the moſt part <hi>vſe</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Obiect. 2. It is a generall cuſtome.</note> it, few or none <hi>refraine</hi> it, vnleſſe a few <hi>ſingular</hi> ſpirits, too <hi>nice</hi> and <hi>curi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous.</hi> But theſe muſt conſider the preciſe charge of God himſelfe, <note place="margin">Anſvver.</note> 
               <hi>Exod.</hi> 23. 2. <hi>Thou ſhalt not follow a multitude to doe euill.</hi> For by <hi>multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Exod. 23. 2. <hi>Multitudo pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cantium pecca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum exaggerat, non extenuat.</hi> Muſc. app. ad Pſal. 15. de Iur. Gen. 37. 20. 1 King. 18. 22. Ierem. 44. 15. Acts 7. 57. Matth. 27. 22.</note> of ſinners, the ſinne is <hi>aggraua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted,</hi> not <hi>extenuated.</hi> It excuſed not the <hi>inhumanitie</hi> of <hi>Ioſephs</hi> brethren, nor the <hi>Idolatrie</hi> of <hi>Baal</hi> Prophets, nor the <hi>obſtinacie</hi> of thoſe that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood <hi>Ieremiah,</hi> nor the <hi>crueltie</hi> of thoſe that ſtoned <hi>Steuen,</hi> nor the <hi>impietie</hi> of thoſe that crucified <hi>Chriſt.</hi> In euery one of theſe, moſt voices carried it, yet was not the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence any whit the leſſe.</p>
            <p>And as it <hi>excuſeth</hi> not from <hi>ſinne,</hi> ſo it <hi>exempteth</hi> not from <hi>iudgement.</hi> It ſaued not the <hi>olde World</hi> from <note place="margin">Prou. 11. 21. Gen. 7. 23.</note>
               <pb n="79" facs="tcp:18971:44"/>
               <hi>drowning,</hi> nor <hi>Sodome</hi> from <hi>burning,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Gen. 19. 24. Numb. 15. 9.</note> nor the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> from <hi>periſhing.</hi> Nay, the number in all theſe <hi>kindled</hi> Gods <hi>indignation,</hi> and cryed the <hi>lowder</hi> in his eares for <hi>vengeance.</hi> In this caſe then, that <hi>counſell</hi> of one is good, <hi>Liue as a few, that with a few thou mayſt walke worthy of Gods</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Viue vt pauci, vt cum paeucis inueniri merea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris in regno Dei,</hi> Caſsian. Matt. 7. 13.</note> 
               <hi>Kingdome.</hi> And that of our Sauiour, <hi>Enter in at the ſtraight gate.</hi> Alleadge not the <hi>number</hi> of Swearers to <hi>iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie</hi> thy ſwearing: though it be the <hi>broad way,</hi> walke not in it. Colde comfort is it to goe to hell for <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panie:</hi> happier ſhall it be for thee to be one of thoſe <hi>few,</hi> that had rather haue their <hi>ſoules</hi> drop out of their <hi>bodies,</hi> then a <hi>vaine Oath</hi> out of their <hi>mouthes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But it will thirdly be <hi>obiected;</hi> they <note place="margin">Obiect. 3. They haue no euill minde or intent.</note> do it from <hi>no bad mind,</hi> no <hi>wicked in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent:</hi> but their hearts are <hi>good,</hi> they meane vvell, and therefore to be borne with. But this <hi>excuſe</hi> is both <note place="margin">Anſvver. This excuſe is 1 Friuolous.</note> 
               <hi>friuolous,</hi> and <hi>falſe.</hi> Firſt, <hi>friuolous,</hi> and that to no purpoſe: for <hi>by thy</hi>
               <pb n="80" facs="tcp:18971:45"/>
               <hi>words thou ſhalt be iuſtified, and by</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Matth. 12. 37.</note> 
               <hi>thy words thou ſhalt be condemned, Matth.</hi> 12. 37. And if of <hi>euery idle word,</hi> then much more of <hi>idle Oaths</hi> muſt wee giue <hi>account at the day of Iudgement.</hi> Secondly, it is not onely <hi>friuolous,</hi> but falſe: for our <hi>Sauiour</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 Falſe.</note> telleth vs plaine, that <hi>out of the abundance of the hart the mouth ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Matth. 12. 34.</note> 
               <hi>Matth.</hi> 12. 34. The <hi>Treaſure</hi> will be knowne by the <hi>Mettall;</hi> 
               <note place="margin">He that feareth God in heart, cannot abuſe him in vvord.</note> the <hi>Fountaine</hi> by the <hi>Water;</hi> the <hi>Fire</hi> by the <hi>heate;</hi> the <hi>Sunne</hi> by the <hi>light,</hi> the <hi>Tree</hi> by the <hi>fruit.</hi> Canſt thou <hi>feare</hi> God in <hi>heart,</hi> and <hi>abuſe</hi> him in <hi>word?</hi> Can thy minde <hi>bleſſe</hi> him <note place="margin">If the minde bleſſe him, the tongue can not blaſpheme him Iam. 1. 26. Obiect. 4. They ſvveare no deepe but little Oathes. Anſvvere. All vain Oaths are condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, be they great or ſmall.</note> and thy tongue <hi>blaſpheme</hi> him? No, <hi>If thou refraineſt not thy tongue, thy religion is in vaine, Iam.</hi> 1. 26.</p>
            <p>But it will fourthly be <hi>obiected,</hi> they ſweare <hi>no deepe Oathes,</hi> as by <hi>God himſelfe,</hi> or by the <hi>parts</hi> and <hi>ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuncts</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> but <hi>little</hi> Oathes, as <hi>by the Maſſe;</hi> or, <hi>by our Lady;</hi> or, by <hi>faith, troth,</hi> and ſuch like. But euen theſe Oathes will not excuſe: for
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:18971:45"/>
in a <hi>matter of importance,</hi> that requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth <note place="margin">Matt. 5. 37. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Baſil. concion. in Pſal. 15. Svvearing by Faith and Troth, a vaine thing.</note> an Oath, wee muſt (as hath beene ſhewed) vſe <hi>the Name of God.</hi> On the other ſide, in <hi>a trifle</hi> vvee muſt not <hi>ſweare at all:</hi> our <hi>Yea</hi> and <hi>Nay,</hi> (ſaith Chriſt) muſt ſerue the turne. All <hi>vaine</hi> Oathes are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned, be they <hi>deepe</hi> Oathes, or <hi>little</hi> Oathes. And for theſe, if thou beeſt not <hi>ſorrowfull,</hi> &amp; God <hi>mercifull,</hi> thou wilt finde none ſo <hi>little,</hi> but <hi>deep</hi> enough; none ſo <hi>light</hi> but <hi>heauy</hi> enough, none ſo <hi>ſmall,</hi> but <hi>great</hi> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to ſend thee down into hell.</p>
            <p>And as for that common ſwea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring by our <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Troth;</hi> how vaine a thing is it vpon needleſſe oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion? For, our <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Troth,</hi> (as one ſaith) are the <hi>moſt precious Iewels we haue.</hi> Now there is none <note place="margin">A. Dent.</note> but a <hi>banquerupt</hi> that vvill lay the beſt <hi>Iewell</hi> in his houſe to <hi>pawne</hi> for euery ſmall <hi>trifle.</hi> So when wee lay <note place="margin">It ſhevveth vve are banque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupts in truth, and of very ſmall credit.</note> theſe to <hi>gage</hi> for euery vvord vvee ſpeake, it ſheweth we are <hi>banquerupts in truth,</hi> and that we are of very <hi>ſmall</hi>
               <pb n="82" facs="tcp:18971:46"/>
               <hi>credit.</hi> Otherwiſe wee would not bring forth theſe <hi>precious Iewels</hi> but vpon ſome waightie occaſion.</p>
            <p>But it will fiftly be <hi>obiected,</hi> they ſweare <hi>no lye,</hi> but that which is <hi>true,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Obiect. 5. They ſvveare no lye, but truth. Anſvver.</note> and they know to be <hi>certaine.</hi> To vvhich I anſwere: firſt, if it be ſo, it needeth no Oath: our faithfull word may ſerue in ſtead of an Oath. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Euangelica ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritas non recipt iuramentum, cum omnis ſermo fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delis pro iureiu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rando ſit.</hi> Hier. in Mat. 5. 34. Zach. 5. 4. Exod. 20. 7.</note> For God hath threatned, as to pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh him, that <hi>ſweareth by his name falſely,</hi> ſo not to <hi>hold him guiltleſſe that taketh his name vainely.</hi> So that there is a <hi>curſe</hi> for him that ſwea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth, <note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Siue mendaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, ſiue inutili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</hi> Lyra in his <hi>Gloſſe</hi> on Eccl. 23. 10.</note> 
               <hi>whither falſely, or to no pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, I anſwere with <note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ex ſaepe, mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tumque iurando, naſcitur &amp; per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuriu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; impie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas,</hi> Phil. lib. de dee. praec.</note> 
               <hi>Philo Iudaeus, that of much and often ſwea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring commeth both periurie and impie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie.</hi> And with that learned Father, S. <note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>Nemo eſt qui frequenter iurat, qui aliquando non peierat: ſicut qui conſueuit multa loqui, aliquando loquitur importuna.</hi> Au. in Mat. 5</note> 
               <hi>Auguſt. none there is that often ſweareth, but ſometimes hee forſwea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth: euen as hee that is wont to ſpeake much doth ſometime ſpeake out of ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.</hi>
               <pb n="83" facs="tcp:18971:46"/>
And therefore the ſafeſt courſe in this caſe is, to follow the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept of a very <note n="d" place="margin">Menander. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Peri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nder.</note> Heathen Poet, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Shunne</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>an Oath when thou mayſt iuſtly take it.</hi> For ſwearing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getteth <note n="e" place="margin">
                  <hi>Aug.</hi> ad conſ. de mend. c. 15.</note> 
               <hi>facilitie, facilitie cuſtome, cuſtome periurie:</hi> the very <note n="f" place="margin">
                  <hi>Non penitus iurare prohibuit ſed occaſionem periurij euitare docuit.</hi> Greg. in Mat. 5.</note> 
               <hi>occaſion whereof we ſhould ſhunne,</hi> ſaith one. Now, <note n="g" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ceſſet ignis, &amp; incendium non fit ſubtrahe gla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dium, &amp; hornici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dium non permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titur ſic tolle iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ramentum, &amp; periurium non fit.</hi> Chryl. om. 12. op. imp. cap. 52.</note> 
               <hi>put out the fire there can be no flame: take away the ſword, there can be no murther: ſo ſweare not at all, there can be no periurie. Periurie is a dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous pit,</hi> ſaith a <note n="h" place="margin">
                  <hi>Periurium praecititium eſt: qui iurat iuxta eſt, qui non iurat, longe. Falſa iuratio exitioſa, vera periculoſannulla ſecura.</hi> Auguſt in Iacob. 5. 12.</note> Father, <hi>He that ſwea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth is nigh to it, he that ſweareth not farre from it: falſe ſwearing is deadly, true ſwearing dangerous, no ſwearing ſecure:</hi> vvee ſee it true in <note n="i" place="margin">1 Sam. 19. 6. 15.</note> 
               <hi>Saul,</hi> a <hi>horrible ſwearer,</hi> a <hi>damnable forſwea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer,</hi> 1 Sam. 19.</p>
            <p>But it vvill <note n="*" place="margin">Obiect. 6. They ſvveare to be beleeued.</note> ſixtly be <hi>obiected,</hi> they are <hi>vrged</hi> thereunto by <hi>neceſſitie,</hi> they ſhall not otherwiſe be <hi>beleeued.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="84" facs="tcp:18971:47"/>
I anſwere: firſt, ſhall there bee <note place="margin">Anſvvere.</note> any <hi>neceſſitie</hi> to moue thee to grieue <note place="margin">1</note> and diſpleaſe thy Creatour? doeſt <note place="margin">Rather loſecre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit vvith men, then reputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on vvith God.</note> thou preferre thy credit <hi>with men,</hi> before thy reputation <hi>with God?</hi> Surely, in this caſe thou ſhouldeſt rather chuſe not at all to be <hi>cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dited.</hi> Better that men <hi>vniuſtly</hi> ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect thee, then God <hi>iuſtly</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne thee. <note place="margin">2</note>
            </p>
            <p>But ſecondly, in ſaying they will <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Aut parum bene ſentit qui iurat, de eo cui iurat, aut diffidit is, qui iuramentum exigit.</hi> Pellic. ſuper. Matth.</note> not elſe <hi>beleeue thee,</hi> thou art <hi>vncha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritable to others,</hi> and <hi>ſhameſt thy ſelfe. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncharitable to others,</hi> in cenſuring them as diſtruſtfull and ſuſpicious of thee, which argueth themſelues alſo to be <hi>guiltie</hi> of falſehood. <note place="margin">1</note> 
               <hi>Shameſt thy ſelfe,</hi> in that thy credit <note place="margin">2</note> is ſo crackt, thy word is not any <note place="margin">It is a ſhame to our ſelues, that vve are not beleeued.</note> thing vvorth without an Oath. For therefore thou ſweareſt, becauſe thy ſimple vvord is of no credit. And what is the cauſe men are ſo <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>credulous</hi> 
               <note place="margin">The cauſe of others in cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulitie is our falſehood.</note> and <hi>ſuſpicious</hi> of thee? It is thy <hi>wauering</hi> in thy <hi>words,</hi> thy <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit</hi> in thy <hi>dealings,</hi> thy <hi>vnfaithfulnes</hi>
               <pb n="85" facs="tcp:18971:47"/>
in thy <hi>promiſes,</hi> thy <hi>falſehood</hi> in thy <hi>ſayings,</hi> thy <hi>inconſtancy</hi> in thy <hi>ſpeeches.</hi> No maruell then, thy ſaying is ſo little reſpected: vvouldeſt thou on the other ſide haue thy vvord <hi>cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dited?</hi> I ſhall tell thee a farre better <note place="margin">The beſt vvay to be credited, is to be true &amp; vnblamable in all our dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings.</note> way then ſwearing. Be <hi>true</hi> and <hi>vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blamable</hi> in all thy dealings, and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the rule Saint <hi>Ierome</hi> giueth <hi>(quae dixeris, putes iurata)</hi> that which thou haſt ſpoken, ſuppoſe it as <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hieron. ad Celan.</hi> Be true
in <list>
                     <item>Heart,</item>
                     <item>Words,</item>
                     <item>Workes.</item>
                  </list>
               </note> ſworne. <hi>Meane</hi> not <hi>cunningly, ſpeake</hi> not <hi>diſſemblingly, deale</hi> not <hi>deceit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully:</hi> but be <hi>ſincere</hi> in <hi>heart, true</hi> in <hi>words, faithfull</hi> in <hi>workes.</hi> So ſhall men credit thy bare <hi>ſaying,</hi> more then anothers <hi>ſwearing:</hi> for it is <hi>not the Oath</hi> (ſaith one) <hi>that gineth</hi> 
               <note place="margin">I. D.</note> 
               <hi>credit to a man, but a man to his Oath.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So then, thy common ſwearing <note place="margin">1</note> is to no purpoſe at all: for if thou <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Quid enim opus eſt iuramento, vnoquo<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> de alio optime &amp; ſenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ente &amp; ſperante.</hi> Pellic.</note> beeſt knowne to be vpright in words, and deeds, thy word ſhall goe currant, and decide any mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, inaſmuch as thou makeſt more
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:18971:48"/>
account of that, then another of his Oath.</p>
            <p>If on the other ſide, to vſe <hi>dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble</hi> 
               <note place="margin">An honeſt mans vvord is better reſpect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed then a dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble-dealers Oath.</note> 
               <hi>dealing,</hi> that cauſeth thy very <hi>Oath</hi> to be <hi>ſuſpected,</hi> and not ſo much <hi>reſpected</hi> as an honeſt mans <hi>Word.</hi> And ſurely wee may vvell <hi>ſuſpect</hi> a common <hi>Swearer:</hi> for <hi>(qui deierat, peierat) Hee that often</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ioh. Dow.</note> 
               <hi>ſweareth, often forſweareth.</hi> And wee haue little cauſe to <hi>beleeue</hi> ſuch a one: for (as <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>W. W.</hi> on <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 4. 2. Svvearing and Lying are In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mates.</note> one ſaith well to this purpoſe) <hi>Swearing and Lying for the moſt part are In-mates, and dwell both vnder one roofe, and walke hand in hand, like the Theefe and the Receiuer; or as the Vſurer and the Broker.</hi> It is to be feared, that a common <hi>Swearer</hi> is a <hi>Lyer:</hi> he that feareth not <hi>the one,</hi> feareth not <hi>the other:</hi> hee that will <hi>diſhonour God,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Hee that vvill diſhonor God, vvill deceiue his neighbour.</note> will <hi>deceiue his neighbour:</hi> hee that maketh no <hi>Conſcience</hi> of the <hi>first Table,</hi> will not make any <hi>Conſcience</hi> of the <hi>ſecond.</hi> If thou beeſt not then <hi>beleeued,</hi> the more is thy <hi>ſhame,</hi>
               <pb n="87" facs="tcp:18971:48"/>
the <hi>diſgrace</hi> is thine owne, and <hi>blame</hi> thy ſelfe for it.</p>
            <p>But it will ſeauenthly be <hi>obiected</hi> of others, they confeſſe this ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narie <note place="margin">Obiect. 7. They doe it onely in their anger.</note> ſwearing to be <hi>haynous</hi> and <hi>grieuous:</hi> onely now and then they are <hi>moued</hi> thereunto in <hi>their anger,</hi> when they are <hi>croſſed</hi> and <hi>offended,</hi> and then they cannot refraine them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues.</p>
            <p>But this is the worſt <hi>excuſe</hi> of all <note place="margin">Anſvvere. Such as pleade this, are like fooles and mad-men.</note> the former: and ſuch as theſe I can compare to none ſo fitly as to <hi>fooles</hi> or <hi>mad-men,</hi> who (as wee ſay) if they be ſtricken, <hi>ſtrike their next fellowes.</hi> Theſe, in farre vvorſe <note place="margin">For the vvrongs they receiue of men, they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenge them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues vpon God.</note> manner, doe for the <hi>diſpleaſure</hi> and <hi>wrongs</hi> they receiue <hi>of men, reuenge</hi> themſelues <hi>vpon God.</hi> If vpon the leaſt occaſion they be <hi>moued</hi> and <hi>prouoked,</hi> then by a <hi>multitude of Oathes,</hi> they ſet vp (as it were) their Flagge of defiance <hi>againſt Heauen,</hi> and proclaime warre <hi>againſt Chriſt,</hi> it ſhall coſt him a <hi>Stab,</hi> as though hee were the ſole cauſe of their
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:18971:49"/>
diſcontentment. The like they doe <note place="margin">The like they doe in their ſports and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creations.</note> in their <hi>ſports</hi> and <hi>recreations:</hi> let them be <hi>croſſed</hi> in their carding, dicing, bowling, or any other <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtime,</hi> they ſpit out their venome <note place="margin">If they be croſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in them, God ſhall be croſſed in his honour.</note> againſt the <hi>Lord of glory:</hi> and if they indure any loſſe, they will make God himſelfe pay for it. So prone and ready they are to diſhonour <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Tam facile, &amp; pronum eſt ſupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ros contemnere teſtes.</hi> Iuuen.</note> God.</p>
            <p>But oh vile wretched Creature, whoſoeuer thou art: why ſhouldeſt thou thus, like a <hi>mad Dogge,</hi> flye <note place="margin">Like mad-dogs they flye in their maſters face vvho fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth them.</note> in the face of thy <hi>Maſter</hi> that fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth thee, eaſing thy ſtomacke vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his ſacred <hi>Name,</hi> whenſoeuer thou art <hi>grieued</hi> and <hi>offended?</hi> Hee neuer did thee <hi>hurt,</hi> but hath euer <note place="margin">And neuer did them hurt, but good. Acts 17. 28.</note> beene a <hi>gracious</hi> God vnto thee, in whom thou <hi>liueſt</hi> and <hi>moueſt,</hi> and from whom thou enioyeſt all things, and of whom, and whoſe <hi>mercy it is,</hi> that <hi>thou art not conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med:</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Lamen. 3. 22.</note> and wilt thou make him this requitall? Muſt others <hi>wrongs</hi> be <hi>reuenged</hi> on him? for by thy <hi>Hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh</hi>
               <pb n="89" facs="tcp:18971:49"/>
               <hi>Oathes</hi> thou <hi>hurteſt</hi> not them, <note place="margin">By their helliſh Oathes they hurt not others but God and their ovvne ſoules:</note> thou <hi>hurteſt</hi> thinc owne ſoule, thou <hi>hurteſt</hi> and <hi>diſhonoureſt</hi> God. Hee it is that is <hi>prouoked,</hi> and his holy <hi>Spirit</hi> is <hi>grieued,</hi> as thou ſhalt one day know, and feele to thy vvoe, without vnfained repentance.</p>
            <p>But it will laſtly be <hi>obiected,</hi> they vtterly <hi>deteſt</hi> it, and when they haue <note place="margin">Obiect. 8. They ſvveare by reaſon of cuſtome.</note> done it at vnawares, they <hi>deſire</hi> God to <hi>pardon</hi> it: but they haue got a fooliſh <hi>cuſtome,</hi> and they cannot <hi>leaue</hi> it.</p>
            <p>I anſwere firſt, in that they ſay <note place="margin">1</note> they <hi>deteſt</hi> it, it appeareth to be <note place="margin">Anſvvere. Did they hate it, they vvould not continue in it.</note> falſe. Were it ſo, they would not make a trade of ſuch a knowne ſinne; nay, they would neuer be at reſt and quiet, vntill they were well wained from it. And what if (when <note place="margin">Their asking forgiueneſſe ſhall not excuſe them.</note> they haue ſworne) they <hi>deſire par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don;</hi> will God heare and accept ſuch a Prayer? Can they hope, hee will <hi>forgiue</hi> it, when they ſtill <hi>continue</hi> 
               <note place="margin">They are here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in like the Ievves. Mark. 15. 18.</note> in it? what are they herein, but like the <hi>Iewes</hi> who deſpightfully <hi>cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied</hi>
               <pb n="90" facs="tcp:18971:50"/>
Chriſt, and yet in words <hi>ſalute</hi> him, with <hi>Haile King of the Iewes.</hi> So for theſe, to make a <hi>Prayer</hi> like a flaſh of <hi>Lightening,</hi> and yet <hi>conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually</hi> 
               <note place="margin">It is no other thing but a mocking of God. Gal. 6. 7.</note> without ceaſing to <hi>grieue</hi> God by this ſin; what is it elſe but a <hi>moc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king</hi> of God, who <hi>will not be mocked, Gal.</hi> 6.</p>
            <p>Secondly, in that they pleade <note place="margin">2</note> long <hi>cuſtome,</hi> they doe not at all <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hoc eſt ſeipſum accuſare, magis quam excuſare, &amp;c.</hi> Muſc. app. ad Pſal. 15. de Iur.</note> 
               <hi>excuſe,</hi> but the more <hi>accuſe</hi> them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues. For, it is as if the <hi>Theefe</hi> ſhould <hi>pleade</hi> at the <hi>Barre,</hi> that hee hath beene ſo long <hi>accuſtomed</hi> to <hi>robbing,</hi> that hee cannot <hi>leaue</hi> it. Would the <hi>Iudge</hi> take this <hi>excuſe</hi> 
               <note place="margin">It vvill not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe a theefe, but the ſooner condemne him.</note> for good? or not rather the ſooner <hi>condemne</hi> him, as more iuſtly deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing to be <hi>hanged?</hi> And can vvee thinke, that the Lord will <hi>acquit</hi> ſuch notorious <hi>Fellones,</hi> as make it a daily practiſe to <hi>robbe</hi> him, and <note place="margin">Hovv then can God acquit ſuch as daily robbe him of his glory?</note> to <hi>bereaue</hi> him of his deareſt ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour? wee cannot thinke it. If <hi>cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome</hi> will not <hi>excuſe</hi> the <hi>Theefe</hi> for his <hi>ſtealing,</hi> nor the <hi>Murtherer</hi>
               <pb n="91" facs="tcp:18971:50"/>
for his <hi>killing,</hi> nor the <hi>Adulterer</hi> for his <hi>whoring,</hi> how ſhall it excuſe the <hi>Swearer</hi> for his <hi>ſwearing?</hi> for euery ſinne, by how much the <note place="margin">Euery ſinne, by hovv much the more cuſtoma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, by ſo much the more dete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtable,</note> more <hi>common</hi> and <hi>cuſtomable,</hi> by ſo much the more <hi>haynous</hi> and <hi>dete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtable.</hi> If once to ſweare vainely be a ſinne, then is cuſtomable Swea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring a <hi>crying</hi> ſinne, and muſt needs (being a <hi>higher</hi> treſpaſſe) incurre <note place="margin">And the more damnable.</note> the <hi>higher</hi> condemnation. And ſo much for anſwere to ſuch <hi>Obiecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> as are vſuall in the mouthes of prophane Swearers.</p>
            <p>Wherefore ſeeing the <hi>Reaſons</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Exhortation, To breake off this ſinne.</note> are ſo <hi>forcible</hi> on the one ſide, and the <hi>Excuſes</hi> ſo <hi>friuolous</hi> on the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſide; let euery one endeuour to breake off this ſinne by repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, being <hi>carefull</hi> to <hi>leaue</hi> it, <hi>zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous</hi> to <hi>hate</hi> it, <hi>reſolute</hi> to <hi>forſake</hi> it; to which end, vſe the beſt <hi>meanes</hi> againſt it: as, <note place="margin">Meanes to be vſed againſt it. 1 Bevvare of that vvhich may giue vvay to it, or cauſe it.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>beware of any thing</hi> that may ſeeme to <hi>giue way to it,</hi> as the vſe of earneſt <hi>proteſtations,</hi> which is the
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:18971:51"/>
next doore to it: or any thing that may ſeeme to <hi>cauſe it.</hi> As if it be from a <hi>proud</hi> ſpirit, deſire of <hi>glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry; ſtriue</hi> to <hi>ſubdue</hi> it: if from a <hi>co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uetous</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1</note> ſpirit, <hi>deſire</hi> of <hi>gaine; ſeeke</hi> to <hi>ſuppreſſe</hi> it: if from an <hi>impatient</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2</note> ſpirit, outragious <hi>furie; labor</hi> to <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine</hi> 
               <note place="margin">3</note> it. Take Saint <hi>Iames</hi> coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell, <note place="margin">Iames 1. 19.</note> 
               <hi>Be ſlow to Wrath.</hi> Take Saint <hi>Pauls</hi> counſell, <hi>Be angry, but ſinne</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Epheſ. 4. 26.</note> 
               <hi>not.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, to the end this <note place="margin">2 Bridle thy Tongue, and be vvary ouer it.</note> Sinne may fall into a Conſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>Set a bit in thine owne mouth,</hi> and <hi>curbe</hi> in therewith thy <hi>tongue,</hi> that ſlipperie piece of fleſh, that in this kinde thou <hi>offend not with</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 39. 1.</note> 
               <hi>it.</hi> If thou vvert in <hi>ſuite of Law,</hi> for any matter that concerneth thy <hi>eſtate,</hi> how vvary vvouldeſt thou be ouer thy <hi>words,</hi> leaſt thou ſhouldeſt any vvay wrong thy ſelfe. In this matter that concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth thy <hi>Soule,</hi> bee as <hi>warie</hi> and <note place="margin">Be as vvary as thou vvouldeſt be in a ſuite of Lavv.</note> 
               <hi>watchfull,</hi> leaſt thou <hi>wrong</hi> both <hi>GOD</hi> and <hi>thy ſelfe: GOD,</hi>
               <pb n="93" facs="tcp:18971:51"/>
of his <hi>Glory,</hi> and thy ſelfe of <hi>Heauen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, <hi>haunt not the company of thoſe that vſe it;</hi> but make choiſe <note place="margin">3 Haunt not the company of thoſe that vſe it.</note> of ſuch <hi>company</hi> as vvill rather <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proue</hi> it, and not at any time <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire</hi> it, vnleſſe vpon vrgent <hi>ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitie.</hi> It is a ſinne not a little <hi>conta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious,</hi> the <hi>plague</hi> it ſelfe not more <hi>infectious.</hi> The ſafeſt courſe to eſcape it, is not to come within the aire of it.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, <hi>conſider</hi> ſeriouſly the <note place="margin">4 Conſider the grieuous puniſhments of it.</note> 
               <hi>grieuous puniſhments</hi> that haue fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed vaine ſwearers in all ages, which (being <note n="*" place="margin">Deut. 28. 58. 59. 60. 61.</note> 
               <hi>threatned</hi> alike to all) our ſelues alſo may feare without amendement. Some haue had their <hi>tongues ſwelling,</hi> others their <hi>mouths burning,</hi> ſome haue beene ſtroke madde, others ſuddainly <hi>dead.</hi> In a <note place="margin">Of all other ſinnes, it hath not eſcaped puniſhment.</note> word, of all other ſinners, they haue taſted <hi>iudgements, many</hi> in <hi>number, great</hi> in <hi>meaſure.</hi> And (which is vvorſt of all) to make vp their <hi>Woe,</hi> they haue plunged <hi>Body</hi>
               <pb n="94" facs="tcp:18971:52"/>
and <hi>Soule</hi> into eternall <hi>condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Laſtly, commend thy ſelfe by <note place="margin">5 Deſire God to keepe the doore of thy lips.</note> 
               <hi>prayer vnto Almightie God,</hi> for the helpe and aſſiſtance of his holy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit. He it is, <hi>that worketh in vs both</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Phil. 2. 12.</note> 
               <hi>the will and the deed:</hi> and therefore let <hi>Dauids</hi> deſire be euer thy deſire, <hi>Set a watch, O Lord, before my mouth, and keepe the doore of my lips,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 141. 3.</note> 
               <hi>Pſael.</hi> 141. 3. By theſe <hi>meanes</hi> wee ſhall be the better enabled to <hi>diſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ure</hi> our <hi>tongues</hi> from the <hi>common</hi> vſe of <hi>Oathes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſo much ſhall ſerue to haue ſpoken of the one part of my Text, <hi>Becauſe of Oathes.</hi> It now remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth that I haſten to the other: <hi>The Land mourneth.</hi> In vvhich <note place="margin">The ſecond part; the effect, Mourning.</note> vvordes, there is miniſtred an <hi>Ocean</hi> of matter, vvhich I ſhall <hi>ſwimme</hi> through as faſt as I can, and briefe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly runne ouer it, leſt the time ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runne mee.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Prophet</hi> telleth vs in this lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter part, that the effect of <hi>ſwearing</hi> 
               <note place="margin">The meaning.</note>
               <pb n="95" facs="tcp:18971:52"/>
is <hi>mourning;</hi> by which hee vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandeth not onely <hi>Iudgément,</hi> but <note place="margin">He vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth not only iudgement, but the griefe, and bitternes that follovveth it.</note> the very <hi>griefe</hi> and <hi>bitterneſſe</hi> that followeth of it; becauſe wee are not ſo ſenſible of the <hi>iudgement</hi> it ſelfe, as of the <hi>paine</hi> that waiteth vpon it. The childe would not care for the <hi>rod,</hi> vvere it not for the <hi>ſmart</hi> that commeth after it. No more would vvee at all feare <hi>iudgements,</hi> but that they procure a <hi>feeling,</hi> which is the cauſe of <hi>mourning.</hi> In this terme then here vſed, he giueth vs to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand, <note place="margin">It is ſuch a iudgement, as leaueth a ſting behind it. The doctrines.</note> that it is ſuch a <hi>iudgement</hi> as leaueth a ſting behind it. Hence obſerue the <hi>reward:</hi> firſt, of <hi>ſinne</hi> in <hi>generall:</hi> ſecondly, of vaine <hi>Oathes</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1</note> in <hi>particular.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2</note>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, the <hi>Prophet</hi> here ſheweth <note place="margin">1 The revvard of ſinne in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall. <hi>Sub adulterijs, &amp; periurijs com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehendit alia ſcelera</hi> Ioan Calu. praelect. in hunc locum.</note> vnto vs the reward <hi>of all ſinne:</hi> for <hi>vnder theſe</hi> (ſaith <hi>Caluin) are other ſinnes contained:</hi> for which alſo hee might truely ſay <hi>the Land mourneth;</hi> for what euill euer befell eyther <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon or Nation,</hi> but vvickedneſſe <hi>brought</hi> it, <hi>ſinne</hi> cauſed it? This
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:18971:53"/>
vvas it that cauſed the <note n="a" place="margin">Gen 7. 23.</note> 
               <hi>Floud</hi> to deſtroy the <hi>old World,</hi> 
               <note n="b" place="margin">Gen. 10. 24.</note> 
               <hi>Fire</hi> and <hi>Brimſtone</hi> to conſume <hi>Sodome,</hi> 
               <note n="c" place="margin">Exod. 14. 28.</note> the <hi>Sea</hi> to drowne <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> the <note n="d" place="margin">Numb. 16. 32</note> 
               <hi>Earth</hi> to ſwallow vp <hi>Chorah.</hi> This was it, that was the cauſe of <note n="e" place="margin">Ioſh. 7. 25.</note> 
               <hi>Achans</hi> ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, <note n="f" place="margin">Eſth. 7. 10.</note> 
               <hi>Hamans</hi> hanging, <note n="g" place="margin">Dan. 5. 6.</note> 
               <hi>Belſhaz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zars</hi> trembling, <note n="h" place="margin">Mat. 27. 7.</note> 
               <hi>Iudas</hi> deſpairing. This was it, that barred <note n="i" place="margin">Dan. 4. 30.</note> 
               <hi>Nebuchad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nezzar</hi> out of <hi>mens preſence,</hi> 
               <note n="k" place="margin">Gen. 4. 16.</note> 
               <hi>Cain</hi> out of <hi>Gods preſence,</hi> 
               <note n="l" place="margin">Gen. 3. 24.</note> 
               <hi>Adam</hi> out of <hi>Paradiſe,</hi> 
               <note n="m" place="margin">2 Pet. 2. 4.</note> 
               <hi>Angels out of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen.</hi> And how often did it cauſe God to puniſh his owne people, this people of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> vvho were as the <hi>apple of his eye,</hi> and <hi>ſignet vpon his right hand?</hi> In a word, vvhat need I trauell farre for examples? haue not our ſinnes had the like effect? <note place="margin">Sinne hath cauſed this our Land to mourne, diuers vvayes:</note> haue not they cauſed this our <hi>Land</hi> many times to <hi>mourne?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hath it not ſometime <hi>mourned</hi> by the <hi>Sword,</hi> both (in time paſt) of enemies <hi>openly aſſaulting</hi> it, and <note place="margin">1 By Svvord. Openly.</note> (ſince more lately) of enemies <hi>cloſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vndermining</hi> it, attempting by <note place="margin">Cloſely.</note>
               <pb n="97" facs="tcp:18971:53"/>
               <hi>plots, treaſons,</hi> and <hi>conſpiracies,</hi> to ſubuert <hi>State</hi> and <hi>Religion, Church</hi> and <hi>Common-wealth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hath it not (a ſecond vvay) <hi>mourned</hi> by <hi>Famine,</hi> as many a <note place="margin">2 By Famine.</note> poore Country ſoule can vvitneſſe? hath not GOD depriued them of the <hi>ſtaffe of Bread, made our fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ezek. 4. 16.</note> 
               <hi>Land barren, and the Hearbs</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 107. 34.</note> 
               <hi>of euery Field to wither, for the</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ierem. 12. 4.</note> 
               <hi>wickedneſſe of them that dwell there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hath it not (a third way) <hi>mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned</hi> 
               <note place="margin">3 By Sickenes.</note> by <hi>Sickeneſſe?</hi> euen by the Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtilence, that walketh in the darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and the plague that deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth <note place="margin">Pſal. 91. 6.</note> at noone day, with diuers other ſtrange diſeaſes, which haue (as in <hi>Dauids</hi> time) ſwept away <hi>thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands,</hi> and tenne <hi>thouſands</hi> in our ſtreets?</p>
            <p>Hath it not (a fourth way) <hi>mourned</hi> by <hi>Pouertie?</hi> What mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth <note place="margin">4 By pouertie.</note> then ſuch <hi>crying and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaining</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 144. 14.</note> 
               <hi>in our ſtreetes?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Looke vpon the generall part of
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:18971:54"/>
the Land, doe they not vvant that abundance, they haue formerly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyed? and vvhat a number daily <hi>change,</hi> and <hi>fall</hi> from <hi>proſperitie</hi> to <hi>miſerie,</hi> from <hi>plenty</hi> to <hi>penurie,</hi> from <hi>brauerie</hi> to <hi>beggerie?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hath it not (a fift way) mourned by <hi>vnſeaſonable weather,</hi> quite con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the courſe of nature? hath <note place="margin">5 By vnſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable vvea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</note> not God one while made the <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen as Iron, the Earth as Braſſe,</hi> and the Clouds to denie their moyſture? <note place="margin">Leuit. 26. 19.</note> hath he not another while (and that within the ſpace of theſe few dayes) cauſed the Heauens to <hi>mourne,</hi> and <hi>ſhed teares</hi> by immoderate <hi>ſhowers,</hi> becauſe our hard hearts cannot <hi>mourne:</hi> and the earth to be ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whelmed with <hi>floods</hi> and <hi>invndati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> becauſe of the vniuerſall <hi>flood,</hi> and <hi>deluge</hi> of <hi>ſinne?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Laſtly, to let paſſe other <hi>iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,</hi> and onely to put you in mind <note place="margin">By the death of hopefull Prince <hi>Henry.</hi> Nouemb. 6. 1612.</note> of one more. Hath not the <hi>Land mourned</hi> euer ſince <hi>Nouember</hi> laſt, (my heart melteth to mention it)
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:18971:54"/>
               <hi>by the death of a Prince,</hi> the <hi>glory</hi> of <hi>Peeres,</hi> and <hi>patterne</hi> of <hi>Princes: Prince</hi> HENRY by name; a ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous, a religious, a couragious <hi>Prince,</hi> the very <hi>ioy</hi> of our <hi>hearts,</hi> the <hi>hope</hi> of our <hi>Land,</hi> and our very <hi>ſecuritie,</hi> for the <hi>continuance</hi> of our <hi>peace.</hi> Well, notwithſtanding; the Lord hath taken him from vs, and for our <hi>ſinnes</hi> vvee are of him <hi>depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">For our ſinnes he vvas taken from vs.</note> as of him <hi>vnworthy.</hi> Thankes be vnto God, there is yet a <hi>remnant</hi> 
               <note place="margin">There is yet a remnant of that Princely progeny.</note> of that <hi>Princely</hi> progenie, which the Lord long <hi>preſerue,</hi> and (no doubt) he vvill <hi>preſerue,</hi> if the cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſinnes of the Land, doe not too <note place="margin">And hope there is of the continuance of it.</note> much <hi>prouoke</hi> the fire of his <hi>wrath,</hi> to kindle againſt vs. Hee hath giuen vs hope of it, by the late <hi>marriage</hi> of that <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Freder:</hi> the 5. Count Palatin of the <hi>Rheine,</hi> &amp;c. Princeſſe <hi>Elizab.</hi> Febru. 14. 16<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>2. But yet this is a faire vvar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning.</note> bleſſed couple, the noble <hi>Prince,</hi> and the ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous <hi>Lady,</hi> whom the LORD <hi>increaſe</hi> and <hi>multiply.</hi> But how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer <hi>(Men, Brethren,</hi> and <hi>Fathers,)</hi> this is a faire <hi>warning,</hi> and ſuch a <hi>warning,</hi> as is not too lightly
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:18971:55"/>
to be <hi>paſſed ouer,</hi> and already to be <note place="margin">And to be layd to heart of vs.</note> 
               <hi>forgotten,</hi> as generally it is: but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to <hi>turne our feaſtes into mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and our ſongs into lamentation:</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Amos 8. 10.</note> with <hi>Micah, lamenting like the Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gons, and mourning like the Oſtriches:</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Micah. 1. 8.</note> and taking vp <hi>Ieremiahs</hi> mourne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full complaint, in the laſt of his <hi>Lamentations. The ioy of our heart is gone: our daunce is turned into</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Lament. 5. 15. 16.</note> 
               <hi>mourning: the crowne of our head is fallen: woe now vnto vs that we haue ſinned.</hi> Thus are wee to lay it to heart, and make right <hi>vſe</hi> of it, that ſo God may be pleaſed to <hi>double,</hi> and <hi>trible</hi> his <hi>bleſſings</hi> vpon thoſe <note place="margin">So ſhall God multiply his bleſſings vpon thoſe branches vvhich re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine.</note> goodly <hi>Oliue branches</hi> vvhich re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine, and neuer proceed ſo farre at <hi>controuerſie</hi> with vs, as to turne our <hi>Beth-el</hi> to <hi>Beth-auen,</hi> the houſe of his <hi>Seruice,</hi> to a houſe of <hi>va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And thus wee ſee how <hi>ſinne</hi> hath brought <hi>woe</hi> vpon the <hi>Land;</hi> and how it hath beene the <hi>cauſe</hi> of many a <hi>mourning,</hi> and is yet
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:18971:55"/>
like (if it beare <hi>ſway)</hi> to cauſe many more.</p>
            <p>What ſhould all this teach vs, <note place="margin">Vſe.</note> but 1 to <hi>bewaile</hi> it: 2 to <hi>preuent</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1</note> it: <hi>bewaile</hi> ſinne paſt; <hi>preu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nt</hi> it <note place="margin">2</note> for time to come. Let all <hi>Eſtates,</hi> and <hi>Callings,</hi> from the <hi>higheſt</hi> to <note place="margin">Exhortation to</note> the <hi>loweſt,</hi> leaue and forſake their <hi>darling</hi> ſinnes: <hi>Magiſtrates</hi> their <note place="margin">Magiſtrates.</note> 
               <hi>conniuence,</hi> and too much <hi>win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king: Iudges</hi> their <hi>partialitie,</hi> and <note place="margin">Iudges.</note> too much <hi>fauoring: Patrones</hi> their <note place="margin">Patrones.</note> 
               <hi>theft,</hi> and <hi>Church-robbing: Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Miniſters.</note> their <hi>ſoothing vp,</hi> and <hi>flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering: Lawyers</hi> their <hi>ſubtiltie,</hi> and <note place="margin">Lavvyers.</note> 
               <hi>delaying: Courtiers</hi> their <hi>pollicie,</hi> and <note place="margin">Courtiers.</note> 
               <hi>diſſembling: Citizens</hi> their <hi>pride,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Citizens.</note> and <hi>deceiuing: Gentlemen</hi> their <note place="margin">Gentlemen.</note> 
               <hi>wracking,</hi> and <hi>oppreſſing: Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try-men</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Countrymen. All.</note> their <hi>lawyng,</hi> and <hi>conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding:</hi> and <hi>euery one</hi> of theſe their <hi>coueting.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So ſhall wee haue <hi>beautie for</hi> 
               <note place="margin">So ſhall vvee haue ioy for mourning, Iſa. 61. 3.</note> 
               <hi>aſhes, ioy for mourning, and the garment of gladneſſe for the ſpirit of heauineſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="102" facs="tcp:18971:56"/>
If thus vvith <hi>Niniue</hi> wee repent of <note place="margin">Ionan 3. 10.</note> the euill <hi>againſt God,</hi> God will <hi>repent</hi> of the euill <hi>againſt vs.</hi> If now vvith the <hi>prodigall</hi> childe vve come <hi>to our</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Luke 15. 20. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o ſhall God imbrace vs, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his promiſe vvith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out exception,</note> 
               <hi>ſelue</hi> by <hi>repentance,</hi> our <hi>Father</hi> will <hi>imbrace</hi> vs, and haue <hi>compaſſion</hi> vpon vs, according to his <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe,</hi> his <hi>promiſe</hi> without <hi>exception,</hi> either of <hi>time,</hi> or of <hi>perſons,</hi> or of <hi>ſinnes.</hi> Without <hi>exception</hi> of <hi>time;</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 Of time. Ezek. 18. 27.</note> for hee is ready to doe it <hi>at what time ſoeuer, Ezek.</hi> 18. Without <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception of perſons;</hi> for, <hi>come vnto me</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 Of perſons. Matth. 11. 28.</note> 
               <hi>all heauie laden, Matth.</hi> 11. 28. Without <hi>exception</hi> of <hi>ſinnes;</hi> though they be <hi>crimſon ſinnes,</hi> or <hi>ſcarlet</hi> 
               <note place="margin">3 Of ſinnes. Eſa. 1. 18.</note> 
               <hi>ſinnes, Eſa.</hi> 1. 18.</p>
            <p>But on the other ſide, if our <note n="a" place="margin">Gen. 9. 22.</note> 
               <note place="margin">On the other ſide.</note> 
               <hi>Chams</hi> continue their <hi>ſcoffing,</hi> our <note n="b" place="margin">Heb. 12. 16.</note> 
               <hi>Eſaus</hi> their <hi>prophaning,</hi> our <note n="c" place="margin">Ioſh. 7. 21.</note> 
               <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chans</hi> their <hi>theeuing,</hi> our <note n="d" place="margin">1 Sam. 25. 11.</note> 
               <hi>Nabals</hi> their <hi>coueting,</hi> our <note n="e" place="margin">1 Sam. 18. 9.</note> 
               <hi>Sauls</hi> their <hi>hart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burning,</hi> our <note n="f" place="margin">1 Kings 21.</note> 
               <hi>Ahabs</hi> their <hi>oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing,</hi> our <note n="g" place="margin">2 Kings 9. 22</note> 
               <hi>Iezabels</hi> their <hi>whoring,</hi> our <note n="h" place="margin">Dan 4. 27.</note> 
               <hi>Nebuchadnezzars</hi> their <hi>vaunt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting,</hi> and <hi>all</hi> of vs our <hi>ſinning</hi> and
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:18971:56"/>
               <hi>rebelling</hi> againſt the <hi>King</hi> of <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen:</hi> our <hi>Land</hi> ſhall continue <hi>mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">If vve continue ſinning, our Land ſhall continue mourning.</note> God ſhall continue <hi>ſmiting:</hi> nay, hee vvill bring a greater <hi>plague vpon vs, which wee ſhall not be able to eſcape: his eye ſhall not ſpare vs,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ierem. 11. 11. Ezek. 8. 18.</note> 
               <hi>neither will hee pittie vs, and though wee cry aloud in his eares, hee will not heare vs. Pray</hi> vvee may vvith <hi>Diues,</hi> but not be <hi>heard: Weepe</hi> we <note place="margin">Luke 16. 24. Heb. 12. 17.</note> may with <hi>Eſau,</hi> but not be <hi>pittied: Knocke</hi> wee may vvith the <hi>Virgins,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Matt. 25. 12.</note> but be <hi>denied: Call</hi> vvee may <hi>vpon him, but he will not anſwere: Earely</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Prou. 1. 28.</note> may wee <hi>ſeeke</hi> him, but <hi>we ſhall not finde him.</hi> And ſo much for the firſt thing here obſerued; the <hi>reward of ſinne in generall.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The time being almoſt ſpent, whiſpereth in my eare to <hi>folde vp</hi> that which remayneth in a narrow compaſſe, and to <hi>wind vp</hi> in a word. Many other points there are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hinde: I ſhall but onely name them.</p>
            <p>From the <hi>reward</hi> of <hi>ſinne</hi> in
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:18971:57"/>
generall, vvee ſhould haue come to conſider the <hi>reward of Oathes</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 The revvard of vaine Oaths in particular.</note> in particular, which is the very <hi>bitterneſſe</hi> of <hi>iudgement;</hi> they ſhall end in <hi>mourning.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let ſwearers be as iolly and mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, as they will, they muſt one <note place="margin">Let ſvvearers be as merry as they vvill, they muſt one day mourne: Vnleſſe they preuent it. Matth. 5. 4.</note> day <hi>mourne</hi> for their <hi>mirth;</hi> and happy ſhall it be for them if in this life they may <hi>preuent</hi> it. <hi>Preuent</hi> it they may, if they <hi>mourne</hi> heere. Bleſſed are ſuch, ſaith our <hi>Sauiour, for they ſhall be comforted.</hi> Let them then <hi>lament</hi> it for time paſt, let them <hi>auoyde</hi> it for time to come, and they that <hi>feare</hi> to taſte of this <hi>mourning,</hi> let them <hi>feare</hi> to <hi>ſweare.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hence alſo vvee may note, <note place="margin">Doct. The ground of true mirth is not ſinne, but pietie.</note> (and I ſhall but note it) that the <hi>ground</hi> of true <hi>mirth</hi> is not <hi>ſinne,</hi> but <hi>pietie:</hi> for as <hi>ſinne</hi> is the cauſe of <hi>mourning,</hi> ſo is <hi>godlineſſe</hi> of true <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioycing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whence it followeth; firſt, that <note place="margin">Vſe 1. Only the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly may be true<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly merry.</note> onely the <hi>godly</hi> may be truely <hi>mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie:</hi>
               <pb n="105" facs="tcp:18971:57"/>
for, by Chriſt their <hi>debts</hi> are <note place="margin">Pſal. 103. 3.</note> 
               <hi>paid;</hi> their <hi>Bils</hi> are <hi>cancelled,</hi> and by <note place="margin">Luke 12. 32.</note> God (the beſt <hi>pay-maſter)</hi> they are ſure to be <hi>rewarded;</hi> whence their ioy is <note n="*" place="margin">1 Pet. 1. 8. Phil. 4. 7. 2 The laugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the vvic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked is as the crackling of Thornes.</note> 
               <hi>vnſpeakeable,</hi> and <hi>paſſeth vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding.</hi> Secondly, that the <hi>laughter</hi> of the <hi>wicked</hi> is, but <note n="a" place="margin">Eccleſ. 7. 8.</note> 
               <hi>like the crackling of Thornes,</hi> ſoone ſet on fire, ſoone put out: and that their <hi>Mirth</hi> is but <note n="b" place="margin">Eccleſ. 2. 2. Their ioy like the ioy of a mad-man.</note> 
               <hi>madneſſe,</hi> as <hi>Salomon</hi> tearmeth it: their <hi>ioy</hi> like the <hi>ioy</hi> of a <hi>mad-man,</hi> who <hi>laugheth</hi> when o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers pittie him. <hi>Woe</hi> to ſuch ſaith <hi>Chriſt: for they ſhall waile and weepe. Luke</hi> 6. 25. <note place="margin">Luke 6. 25. The laſt thing, the generalitie of this mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning.</note>
            </p>
            <p>But to haſten from the <hi>Paſſion</hi> to the <hi>Patient,</hi> the laſt thing to be obſerued, is, the <hi>generalitie</hi> of this <hi>Mourning.</hi> It extendeth to the whole Land, it is not <hi>perſonall</hi> but <note place="margin">It is not perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall but natio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall.</note> 
               <hi>nationall. Becauſe of Oathes the Land mourneth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The reaſon is, firſt, becauſe the nature of this ſinne is ſo <hi>horrible,</hi> that GOD thereby is highly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoked to <hi>puniſh</hi> not onely thoſe
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:18971:58"/>
that <hi>commit</hi> it, but euen thoſe that <hi>tollerate</hi> it, whoſe ſinne alſo it is, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <note place="margin">Reaſon 1. <hi>Quatenus,</hi> the vvhole Land doth tolerate it, it is their ſinne.</note> appointed to reforme it. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, becauſe where there is <hi>falſe Swearing;</hi> there the <hi>ſubiect,</hi> and ſo conſequently the whole <hi>Land,</hi> is wronged: and thus <hi>Iustice</hi> b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing <note place="margin">2 Where there is falſe ſvvearing the vvhole land is vvronged, &amp; it cannot ſtand.</note> 
               <hi>ſubuerted,</hi> the <hi>Common-wealth</hi> can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not <hi>ſtand.</hi> Hence may be inferred two concluſions.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1 <hi>The</hi> greatneſſe <hi>of this ſinne.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2 <hi>The</hi> danger <hi>of ſuffering it.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>The <hi>greatneſſe</hi> of it appeareth: <note place="margin">Obſeruat. 1. The greatneſſe of this ſinne: vvhich appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth, 1 By Gods great hatred againſt it. 2 By the great pollution vvhich it vvor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth.</note> firſt, by Gods <hi>great hatred</hi> againſt it, whoſe puniſhment thereof ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taketh the whole <hi>Land:</hi> ſecondly, by the <hi>great pollution</hi> which it wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth, in that it maketh all <hi>obnoxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous,</hi> and is able to pull downe the <hi>vengeance</hi> of GOD, not onely vpon the <hi>Swearers</hi> themſelues, but alſo vpon the vvhole <hi>Land:</hi> and the like doth it alſo vpon the <note place="margin">It pulleth dovvne ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance on the Land,</note> Familie wherein they liue: ſo ſaith
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:18971:58"/>
the Sonne of <hi>Syrach: The plague</hi> 
               <note place="margin">And on the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milie vvhere it is vſed.</note> 
               <hi>ſhall neuer goe from the Swearers houſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, as <hi>great</hi> is the <hi>ſinne,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Eccleſ. 23. 11.</note> ſo <hi>great</hi> is the <hi>danger</hi> of <hi>tollerating</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Obſeruat. 2. The great dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of tollera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting this ſinne in a Common-vvealth.</note> this ſinne in a Common-wealth: for it <hi>eateth</hi> like a <hi>Mothe, fretteth</hi> like a <hi>Canker,</hi> and is the <hi>ruine</hi> of the whole <hi>State</hi> and Kingdome. Hence it followeth,</p>
            <p>Firſt, that <hi>the Magiſtrate is by</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Whence it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lovveth: 1 That the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate is by ſharpe lavves to repreſſe it, <hi>Sueton in vita Auguſt.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>ſharpe lawes to repreſſe it Auguſtus</hi> the <hi>Emperour</hi> gaue charge to the <hi>Pretors</hi> of <hi>Rome (ne paterentur no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men ſuum obſolefieri)</hi> not to ſuffer his name to be worne thread-bare. Such care ſhould <hi>Chriſtian Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates</hi> haue of the <hi>Name</hi> of God, and not <hi>permit</hi> it to be <hi>polluted</hi> by common <hi>Swearing,</hi> a Sinne vſually <note place="margin">Notorious Svvearers pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed of the <hi>Romanes.</hi>
               </note> puniſhed of all Rulers in all <hi>Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons:</hi> as of the <hi>Romanes</hi> with <hi>throw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing downe</hi> from a Rocke: of the <hi>Egiptians</hi> with loſſe of <hi>head:</hi> of the <hi>Grecians,</hi> with loſſe of <hi>Eares:</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Egiptians.</note> of the <hi>Scithians</hi> with loſſe of <hi>goods:</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Grecians.</note> 
               <note place="margin">Scithians.</note>
               <pb n="108" facs="tcp:18971:59"/>
of <hi>Maximilian</hi> the <hi>Emperour,</hi> with <note place="margin">Maximilian.</note> forfeiture of <hi>monie:</hi> of <hi>Iuſtinian</hi> the <note place="margin">Iuſtinian.</note> 
               <hi>Emperour,</hi> with putting to <hi>death:</hi> 
               <note place="margin">K. Lewes.</note> of <hi>King Lewes</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> with ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring <note place="margin">Henry the firſt.</note> their <hi>lips:</hi> laſtly, of <hi>Henry the firſt</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> who ordained with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in his owne <hi>Palace,</hi> for euery <hi>Oath</hi> a <note n="*" place="margin">A Duke, 40. ſhillings; a Lord, tvventie; a Knight, or Gentleman, tenne; a Yeo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, three ſhil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, foure pence; a Page, to be ſcourged.</note> 
               <hi>payment</hi> to the vſe of the poore. It were in like manner to be wiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſome ſharpe <hi>Law</hi> vvere now <hi>enacted</hi> againſt it, in euery both <hi>publike</hi> and <hi>priuate</hi> gouernment: that ſo our <hi>Senatours</hi> might baniſh it out of the <hi>Land,</hi> and our <hi>houſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holders</hi> out of their <hi>Families,</hi> leaſt themſelues alſo come to <hi>ſmart</hi> for it.</p>
            <p>Secondly, hence it followeth, that <note place="margin">2 Svvearers in this kinde are no good Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects.</note> 
               <hi>Swearers in this kinde are no good Subiects.</hi> Good <hi>Subiects</hi> they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be, becauſe they ſinne againſt the whole <hi>Land,</hi> take away the <hi>peace</hi> of it, bring downe <hi>Iudgements</hi> vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it: and ſo commit <hi>Treaſon</hi> not <note place="margin">They commit treaſon againſt the King and State.</note> onely againſt <hi>Chriſt,</hi> but againſt the <hi>King</hi> and <hi>State:</hi> the whole
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:18971:59"/>
               <hi>Land</hi> and <hi>Kingdome</hi> fareth vvorſe for their ſakes. So ſaith the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Ieremiah; Becauſe of Oathes the Land mourneth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And thus (Right Honourable, Right Worſhipfull, and Well-be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued Chriſtians) you haue heard this <hi>Complaint</hi> of <hi>Ieremiah</hi> plainely <hi>handled</hi> vnto you: A <hi>Text</hi> very <note place="margin">This Text is needfull to be handled
in this <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Land.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Citie.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Place.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </note> 
               <hi>needfull</hi> for theſe ſecure times. And therefore pardon mee for making choiſe to ſpeake of no other; euen in this famous <hi>Land,</hi> the <hi>glory</hi> of <hi>Europe:</hi> and in this Mother <hi>Citie,</hi> the <hi>glory</hi> of the <hi>Land:</hi> and in this <hi>publike place</hi> of aſſembly, the <hi>glory</hi> of the <hi>Citie.</hi> And now giue mee leaue to conclude with Applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>Notwithſtanding this ſinne of <hi>Swearing,</hi> hath beene ſhewed to be <note place="margin">Application.</note> to our <hi>Soules</hi> a <hi>Dagger,</hi> to our <hi>Tongues</hi> a <hi>Canker,</hi> and both to our <hi>ſelues</hi> &amp; the <hi>Land</hi> euery way ſo <hi>dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous:</hi> yet if vve take a <hi>ſuruay</hi> of the ſtate of our times, wee ſhall
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:18971:60"/>
finde that herein we come not ſhort <note place="margin">Wee come not ſhort of Iſraell in this ſinne. Mat. 26.</note> of <hi>Iſrael.</hi> Nay, contrariwiſe vvee finde, that it was vſuall with them to <hi>rend their garments</hi> when they heard Gods <hi>name blaſphemed,</hi> which thing (as one ſaith) if wee ſhould <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh. Dow. lect.</hi> on <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 4. 2.</note> doe in our dayes, <hi>wee ſhould neuer goe in whole apparrell,</hi> and the whole wealth of the Land were ſcarce ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient to cloath the people of it. So <note place="margin">It is a ſinne largely ſpread and common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vſed.</note> 
               <hi>largely</hi> is it <hi>ſpread,</hi> and ſo <hi>commonly</hi> is it <hi>vſed:</hi>
               <list>
                  <item>1 <hi>In all Places.</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">1</note>
                  </item>
                  <item>2 <hi>In all Buſineſſes.</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">2</note>
                  </item>
                  <item>3 <hi>Of all Perſons.</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">3</note>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>in all Places:</hi> it <hi>aboundeth</hi> in <note place="margin">1 In all places.</note> the <hi>Court, ſwarmeth</hi> in the <hi>Citie, raigneth</hi> in the <hi>Country.</hi> Secondly, <note place="margin">2 In all buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes.</note> 
               <hi>in all Buſineſſes:</hi> Men cannot <hi>meete</hi> and <hi>part, eate</hi> and <hi>drinke, buy</hi> and <hi>ſell</hi> without it; it is the <hi>Seale</hi> of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery <hi>Bargaine.</hi> Thirdly, <hi>among all</hi> 
               <note place="margin">3 Among all Perſons.</note> 
               <hi>Perſons,</hi> of all <hi>callings</hi> and <hi>conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> whatſoeuer: <hi>Noble-men,</hi> vvho <note place="margin">Noble men.</note> ſhould ſhew by their <hi>Vertue</hi> true
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:18971:60"/>
               <hi>Nobilitie,</hi> and ſhine by their <hi>exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple</hi> to many other, <hi>diſhonour</hi> GOD, and <hi>debaſe</hi> themſelues, becomming <hi>ſlaues</hi> to <hi>Sathan</hi> by this odious ſinne. <hi>Magiſtrates</hi> doe not draw out the Sword againſt it; it walketh <note place="margin">Magiſtrates.</note> 
               <hi>vnpuniſhed, vncontrouled:</hi> nay, them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues are <hi>guiltie</hi> of it, when as they ſhould <hi>correct</hi> it. And herein the <hi>Turkes</hi> doe much out-ſtrip vs, who <note place="margin">Guliel. Tripol.</note> 
               <hi>admit</hi> no idle <hi>Swearer,</hi> of what <hi>qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie</hi> ſoeuer, to any office of <hi>Gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi> From <hi>Magistrates</hi> I had like to haue come to blame the <hi>Tribe</hi> of <hi>Leuy;</hi> and I would to <hi>God</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Miniſters.</note> it were not to be found in ſome of vs: <hi>reformers</hi> of others; herein to be <hi>reformed; Oh tell it not in Gath, nor</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 Sam. 1. 20.</note> 
               <hi>publiſh it in the Streetes of Aſskalon, leaſt the Daughters of the Philiſtines reioyce, leaſt the vncircumciſed tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph.</hi> Paſſe we on to <hi>Gentlemen,</hi> it is <note place="margin">Gentlemen.</note> their greateſt <hi>glory:</hi> the way to ſhew themſelues <hi>generous</hi> and <hi>valorous,</hi> is by ſetting their <hi>Tongues</hi> againſt <hi>Heauen,</hi> and <hi>abuſing</hi> that <hi>Name,</hi> at
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:18971:61"/>
which they ſhould <hi>tremble.</hi> Their <hi>Seruingmen</hi> herein <hi>math</hi> them, if <note place="margin">Seruingmen.</note> not <hi>exceede</hi> them: the <hi>multitude</hi> of <hi>Oathes</hi> (and that from the <hi>baſest</hi> of them) <hi>pierceth</hi> the <hi>Heauens,</hi> and <hi>cryeth</hi> for <hi>vengeance</hi> in the <hi>Eares</hi> of the <hi>Lord</hi> of <hi>Hoſts.</hi> Come wee from them to <hi>Tradeſ-men</hi> both in <note place="margin">Tradeſmen.</note> 
               <hi>Citie</hi> and <hi>Country,</hi> how doe they ſeeke by this ſinne to <hi>gaine the world, and to loſe their owne Soules?</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Mar. 16. 26.</note>
            </p>
            <p>In a word, whom may not God <note place="margin">All ſorts of people.</note> 
               <hi>ſummon</hi> to his <hi>high Court</hi> for this ſinne? <hi>yong</hi> and <hi>old, high</hi> and <hi>low, rich</hi> and <hi>poore, men</hi> and <hi>women, maſters</hi> and <hi>ſeruants, fathers</hi> and <hi>Children,</hi> I, and that young <hi>Infants</hi> before <note place="margin">Yong children.</note> they can <hi>goe</hi> perfectly, or <hi>ſpeake</hi> plainely, or ſcarcely tell their owne <hi>names,</hi> they can readily ſweare by <hi>Gods Name;</hi> and in this they <hi>grew</hi> faſter then in their ſtature. Thus all kindes of perſons <hi>ſeaſon</hi> their <hi>mouthes</hi> with <hi>Oathes:</hi> this <hi>plague</hi> is <hi>rife</hi> in euery part of the <hi>Land:</hi> Where ſhall a man paſſe,
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:18971:61"/>
but hee ſhall hearethem ſent forth out of mens mouthes (like a flocke <note place="margin">A man cannot paſſe, but hee ſhall heare Oathes in eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry place.</note> of Birds) by <hi>hundreds</hi> together? enough to make the <hi>ground</hi> to <hi>cleaue aſunder,</hi> and the <hi>clouds</hi> to <hi>fall</hi> vpon their heads, were not <hi>God</hi> won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull in patience. If they were ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered together as the <hi>frogs</hi> of <hi>Egipt</hi> ſwept vp into an heape, the Land would <hi>ſtincke</hi> of them. Our Oaths, if they were <hi>regiſtred</hi> would fill ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny <hi>volumes:</hi> no maruell, God hath <note place="margin">Volumes of Oathes.</note> for vs a <hi>volume</hi> of <hi>Curſes.</hi> And how doth the <hi>Land</hi> abound with <hi>new</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Zach. 5. 2. 3.</note> 
               <hi>faſhions</hi> of <hi>Oathes,</hi> as well as of <hi>cloathes:</hi> no maruell, we are <hi>puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Nevv faſhions of Oathes.</note> with <hi>new</hi> and <hi>ſtrange</hi> diſeaſes. What ſhould I ſay more of this ſinne? Pardon mee if I cannot <hi>part</hi> with it. If we ſhould <hi>hold</hi> our <hi>peace,</hi> the <hi>ſtones</hi> would <hi>ſpeake.</hi> What good <hi>Minde</hi> can but <hi>grieue</hi> to <hi>conceiue</hi> it? what <hi>Heart</hi> but <hi>bleede</hi> to <hi>thinke</hi> vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it? what <hi>Eye</hi> but <hi>weepe</hi> to <hi>ſee</hi> it? what <hi>Eare</hi> but <hi>tingle</hi> to <hi>heare</hi> it?</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="114" facs="tcp:18971:62" rendition="simple:additions"/>
Well, (to draw to a concluſion) let graceleſſe <hi>Ruffins</hi> runne on in <note place="margin">Exhortation.</note> this finne, let the <hi>moſt part</hi> of men goe on this <hi>broad way,</hi> beloued <hi>(Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Mat. 7. 13.</note> and <hi>Fathers) Wee haue not ſo</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Epheſ. 4. 20.</note> 
               <hi>learned Chriſt.</hi> For vs then, that profeſſe our ſelues <hi>Chriſtians, let vs ſuffer the words of exhortation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And you (my <hi>Lord,</hi> with your <note place="margin">To the Lord Maior, Alder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, and She<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riffes of <hi>London.</hi>
               </note> Honourable Fraternitie on the Bench) let mee the vnworthyeſt of Gods <hi>Meſſengers,</hi> in the feare of God <hi>exhort</hi> you: and let God and his ordinance <hi>preuaile</hi> with you for the <hi>Reformation</hi> of this ſinne, which you haue heard to be no ſmall ſinne, but a <hi>Crimſon Sinne,</hi> a <hi>Scarlet Sinne.</hi> Firſt, be <hi>carefull</hi> to <hi>refraine</hi> it in your ſelues: then bend your <hi>Authoritie</hi> to <hi>reſtraine</hi> it in others. You are Gods <hi>Leiuetenants</hi> here on earth, whom God hath much <hi>aduanced,</hi> and highly <note n="*" place="margin">Pſal. 82. 6.</note> 
               <hi>ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured.</hi> Shew your ſelues truely zealous to <hi>honour</hi> him againe, in <hi>drawing</hi> the <hi>ſword</hi> againſt ſuch as
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:18971:62"/>
               <hi>diſhonour</hi> him. So ſhall hee put vp his <hi>Sword</hi> drawne againſt the <hi>Land.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And you (Right Worthy <hi>Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens)</hi> whom God hath wonderfully <note place="margin">To the Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens.</note> bleſſed with meanes both for this life and a better; be exhorted to <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme</hi> this haynous ſinne: <hi>Cleanſe</hi> it out of your <hi>Streetes: ſweepe</hi> it out of your <hi>Shops: baniſh</hi> it out of your <hi>houſes:</hi> and <hi>grieue not</hi> here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by <note place="margin">Epheſ. 4. 30.</note> 
               <hi>the holy Spirit of God, by which you are ſealed vnto the day of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">To Courtiers.</note>
            </p>
            <p>In a word, <hi>Courtiers, Students,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Students.</note> 
               <note place="margin">Gentlemen.</note> 
               <hi>Gentlemen, Country men, All,</hi> let <note place="margin">Country-men. All.</note> mee <hi>beſeech</hi> you in the <hi>Name</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> and in the <hi>bowels</hi> of <hi>Chriſt Ieſus,</hi> as you tender the <hi>Glory</hi> of GOD, the <hi>Peace</hi> of the <hi>Land,</hi> and the <hi>Saluation</hi> of your <hi>Soules;</hi> doe not runne on head-long in this Sinne of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>aine Swearing:</hi> neyther <note n="*" place="margin">Non libenter cum voluntate, frequenter cum aſſiduitate, men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daciter. cum fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitate, inutiliter ſine neceſſitate, fallaciter cum arte verborum, praecipita<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ter ſine diſcretione, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiter ex liuere.</note> 
               <hi>wilfully,</hi> nor <hi>cuſtoma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly,</hi> nor <hi>falſely,</hi> nor <hi>vainely,</hi> nor <hi>deceitfully,</hi> nor <hi>raſhly,</hi> nor <hi>wickedly:</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Iacob. de Gor.</note>
               <pb n="116" facs="tcp:18971:63"/>
but feare the <hi>Glorious Name</hi> of GOD, and vſe your <hi>Tongues,</hi> as <hi>Trumpets</hi> of his Prayſes. So ſhall the <hi>Land</hi> ceaſe <hi>mourning,</hi> your ſelues eſcape <hi>puniſhing,</hi> and the Gates of <hi>Heauen</hi> ſhall be ſet open vnto you, to the vnchangeable <hi>happineſſe</hi> of your ſoules. Which the Lord God grant vnto vs all, to our eternall ioy and comfort.</p>
            <p>And wee beſeech thee, O Lord, <hi>who workeſt in vs both the will and the deede, Set a watch before our</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Phil. 2. 13.</note> 
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 141. 3.</note> 
               <hi>Mouthes, keepe the doore of our Lips:</hi> Bridle our <hi>Tongues</hi> vvith the <hi>Bit</hi> of thy <hi>Feare:</hi> Cauſe vs to make <hi>account</hi> of thy <hi>holy Name,</hi> and in <hi>this Life</hi> to <hi>honour</hi> thee, that in the <hi>Life to come,</hi> vvee may be <hi>honoured</hi> of thee, in thy eternall Kingdome.</p>
            <p>And Lord, be good vnto our Nation, <hi>viſite</hi> thy <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ine,</hi> thou haſt planted amongſt vs. <hi>Let not the</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 80. 3.</note> 
               <hi>wilde Bore out of the Wood deſtroy it, nor the wilde Beaſts of the Field eate</hi>
               <pb n="117" facs="tcp:18971:63"/>
               <hi>it vp:</hi> But ſpare vs, O Lord, ſpare vs, and <hi>lift vp the light of thy coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 4. 6.</note> 
               <hi>vpon vs. Poure out thy</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ier. 10. 25.</note> 
               <hi>Wrath vpon the Heathen, that haue not knowne thee, and vpon the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miles that haue not called vpon thy Name:</hi> but <hi>proſper</hi> them that ſeeke the <hi>proſperitie</hi> of <hi>Sion:</hi> heare thoſe <note place="margin">Pſal. 122. 6.</note> that <hi>pray</hi> for the <hi>Peace</hi> of <hi>Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem: forgiue</hi> the crying <hi>ſinnes</hi> of the <hi>Land, remoue</hi> thy <hi>Iudgements</hi> that hang ouer it: and <hi>walke thou</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Reuel. 1. 13.</note> 
               <hi>in the midst of the Golden Candle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtickes:</hi> let the Bels of <hi>Aaron</hi> ring long amongſt vs: ſtill <hi>continue</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 Theſ. 3. 1.</note> and <hi>inlarge</hi> the free paſſage of thy <hi>Goſpell. Crowne</hi> with <hi>Bleſſings</hi> our <hi>Soueraigne,</hi> and his <hi>Seede</hi> for euer, that ſo thy <hi>Glory</hi> (O GOD) may <hi>reſt</hi> in our <hi>Land,</hi> till wee all come to <hi>reſt</hi> in the <hi>Land</hi> of <hi>Glory.</hi> Sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie the <hi>Court,</hi> bleſſe the <hi>Citie,</hi> be good to the <hi>Country,</hi> be mercifull to <hi>vs all,</hi> that when wee come to the <hi>end</hi> of our <hi>dayes,</hi> wee may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue the <hi>end</hi> of our <hi>hope, the ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation</hi>
               <pb n="118" facs="tcp:18971:64"/>
               <hi>of our Soules.</hi> Theſe things wee begge in the Name of thy Sonne and our <hi>Sauiour,</hi> to <hi>whom,</hi> with <hi>thee,</hi> and thy holy <hi>Spirit,</hi> be aſcribed all praiſe, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, and glory, now and for euermore. Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:18971:64"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
